Councilman Escabel, is that you?
>> Yes, it is.
>> Okay, great. It says Zoom user tonight,
so you're all over the place. Oh,
>> okay.
>> Thank you.
recording in progress.
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen. I
would like to call the June 8th meeting
of the governing body to order and ask
the clerk to please take the role.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> here.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> present.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> present.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> here.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> present. Mayor Collins,
>> present.
>> Dr. Mr. Emmens
>> present. Mr. Esel
>> here.
>> Mr. Leborn
>> All members are present. We do have a
quorum.
>> Would you please join me in the pledge
of allegiance?
>> Pledge allegiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands, one nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
Consent agenda. All agenda items listed
with the designation of CA are
considered to be routine items by the
governing body and will be enacted by
one motion. There will be no separate
discussion on these items unless a
member of the governing body so requests
and support by two other members is
received. Any item removed from the
consent agenda will be considered in its
normal sequence on the agenda. All
right. Are there any items a member of
this governing body would like to remove
from the consent agenda?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, number 27, please.
>> Those are the BOPU's debts.
>> Concur.
>> And also number one, 41.
>> I'm sorry. 41 a
>> Oh, sorry. Thank you.
So, we're
>> You'd like to remove 27? All right,
we'll move 27. Anybody else?
>> Uh,
>> Mr. Mayor?
>> Yes, Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, I'd like to um
ask to remove um item 28, please.
>> Concur.
>> That's the uh due diligence for the
Belvore Ranch. We'll remove 28.
>> Anybody else?
>> Mr. Mayor?
>> Yes, sir.
[snorts and clears throat] Number 42D,
please.
>> That's the HDR contract for 18th Street.
>> Concur.
>> 42 Delta.
All right, we'll remove 42D.
>> All right,
number 27.
42D.
>> All right. Is there anybody else
>> hearing? None. I would entertain a
motion.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved by Mr. White, seconded
by Dr. Aldridge.
All those in favor of the consent agenda
with 27, 28, and 42D removed, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The consent agenda is
approved with 27, 28, and 42D. They'll
be considered in their normal sequence
on the agenda.
>> Number 6A, public hearing for proposed
budgets for the city of Cheyenne and
Board of Public Utilities for fiscal
year 2027.
All right,
Madam Treasurer, did you have anything
you want to say before you open it up to
the public?
>> You don't have to.
>> Um, no, I do not.
>> Okay, we'll open it up to the public and
see if anybody here would like to speak
to the uh proposal for the budget for
the city of Cheyenne or the Board of
Public Utilities.
Anybody?
All right,
Jennifer, anybody online?
Nope. All right. Anybody on the
governing body?
All right. The purpose of the public
hearing has been met. Next item, please.
6B. Public hearing to determine whether
compliance of annexation conditions
required by Wyoming statute 15-1-402
exists for about 2.69 acres of land
south of Charles Street, east of Wanandi
Avenue, and west of McKinley Avenue.
>> All right. Before we open it up for a
public hearing, we'll get a quick staff
report, please.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, members of the council,
Morgan Dennis, Planning and Development.
This is an annexation for roughly 2.69
acres of land generally located south of
Charles Street, east of Wendy Avenue,
and west of Mckenley Avenue. The city
received a petition to annex this land
from the owners, which was filed with
the city clerk on April 8th, 2026. This
petition was certified by the city clerk
as containing the necessary signatures
according to state statute on April
10th, 2026.
This public hearing is being held in
accordance with Wyoming state statute
15-1-42A.
Pursu pursuant to fulfilling the
requirements in the state statute, staff
asked the governing body to consider the
following. The land proposed to be
annexed is contiguous to the current
city limits. Specifically, the property
is 72% contiguous.
All city services and utilities
currently available to residents of the
city will be provided to the residents
of the annex land. Extending water and
sewer will increase the health and
safety of the residents living in this
area of the community.
The area to be annexed is partly inside
the urban service boundary and is
designated as mixeduse residential by
the future land use map. This type of
development is best supported by being
within city limits and by connecting to
city services.
A certified mailing was sent to all land
owners and utilities within the annex
area not less than 20 days business days
prior to the public hearing.
According to the city's calendar, 20
business days prior to today's hearing
was May 12th, 2026.
The certified mailing was sent out on
May 8th, 2026, and the earliest
confirmation of receipt was dated May
11th, 2026. Property owners within 300
ft of the subject property were also
mailed public notice within the same
time period. This annexation is
accompanied by an assigned zoning
ordinance. Na
>> Morgan, thank you. Did anybody on the
governing body have a question for our
staff?
All right, Morgan. Thank you. How about
anybody in the audience who would like
to speak to the uh proposed annexation
by the owner of the property? Um,
anybody?
>> Jennifer.
>> Yes, Jennifer.
>> Mr. Brian Pixley, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Brian, are you there?
>> Okay. Okay. Can you hear me now? Can you
hear me now?
>> Yep. If you could just tell us your
name.
>> Uh Brian Pixley. How you guys doing
today? You probably you probably see me
a lot uh through all these meetings and
everything.
>> What can we do for you, sir?
>> Yeah. I just like to, you know, uh I'm
I'm totally against all with the all
these uh data centers, you know. Uh I
live off of uh uh Happy Jack Road. And
>> Mr. Pixley, we're talking about an
annexation. Are you talking to us about
the annexation, sir?
Uh yeah, I just wanted you know just uh
I don't support the annexation. So thank
you.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Anybody else? Jennifer,
>> nobody else in the audience. We'll close
that and ask if there anybody in the
governing body would like to uh speak to
us under this public hearing.
All right, hearing none. We'll take the
next item, please.
6 C public hearing to determine whether
compliance of annexation conditions
required by Wyoming statute 15-1-42
exist for about 26.29 acres of land
located northwest of the intersection of
Clear Creek Parkway and Ganet Peak
Drive.
>> Mr. White,
>> mayor and members of Council, Connor
White Planning and Development
Department, the annexation is for
roughly 26.29 29 acres of land generally
located northwest of the intersection of
Clear Creek Parkway and Grant and Ganet
Peak Drive. The city received a petition
to annex the land from the owners uh
which was filed with the city clerk on
April 9th, 2026. The petition was
certified by the city clerk as
containing the necessary signatures
according to state statute on April
10th, 2026.
The public hearing is being held in
accordance with Wyoming state statute
15142A.
Pursuant to fulfilling the requirements
in state statute, staff asks the
governing body to uh consider the
following. The land proposed to be
annexed is contiguous to current city
limits. Specifically, the property is
53.94
uh% contiguous.
Uh all city services and utilities
currently available to properties within
the city will be provided to the annex
land. Extending water and sewer will
increase the health safety health and
safety of individuals living or working
uh in this area of the community.
The area to be annexed is inside the
urban service boundary and designated
with mixeduse employment um and a slight
tiny little bit bit of open space um by
the future land use map. This type of
development is best supported by being
within city limits and connecting to
city services.
Certified mailing was sent to all land
owners, utility and utilities within the
annexed area not less than 20 business
days prior to uh the public hearing.
According to the calendar, 20 business
days prior to the public hearing was May
12th and the certified mailing was sent
out on May 7th. The earliest confirmed
receipt was dated May 11th and property
owners within 300 feet of the subject
property were also mailed notice. Uh
this annexation is accompanied by an
assigned uh zoning ordinance and there
is a zone change request that
encompasses this property proposed for
annexation but it also encompasses a
larger area. So it's not just specific
to this property on its own. And with
that I am available for any questions.
>> Mr. White, thank you. Anybody in the
governing body have a question for
staff?
>> Yes, sir. Dr. Aldridge,
>> Mayor Collins, for you. I'm just
wondering if um we have had any comments
or anyone call the office to make
comments about this annexation.
>> Mayor you um to Dr. Aldrich, no. For
this annexation, we have not had any
phone calls um or anything of that
nature for this annexation.
>> Anyone else?
>> Thank you, Connor. Anybody in the
audience want to speak to the annexation
of these 26.29 29 acres.
Okay. Hearing none, we'll go back to the
governing body. Anybody last comment on
the annexation?
Hearing none. The purpose of the public
hearing has been met and we'll move on
to the next item, please. Number 6D,
public hearing to determine whether
compliance of annexation conditions
required by Wyoming statute 15-1-42
exist for about 3,459.99
acres of land located east of South Gley
Highway and south of the Sweetgrass
subdivision.
>> All right, before we uh go out to the
public, we'll go for a staff report. Mr.
White,
>> mayor, member count, members of council,
Connor White, Planning and Development
Department.
This annex stationation is for roughly
3,459.99
acres of land generally located east of
South Gley Highway and south of the
Sweetgrass subdivision.
The city received petition to annex this
land from the owners which was filed
with the city clerk on April 9th and the
petition was certified by the city clerk
as containing the necessary signatures
according to state statute on April
10th.
Pursuant to fulfilling the requirements
of state statute, staff asks the
governing body to consider the
following. The land proposed to be
annexed is contiguous to current city
limits. Specifically, the property is
45.63%
contiguous.
All city services and utilities
currently available uh to properties uh
within the city will be provided to the
annex land. Extending water and sewer
will increase the health safety health
and safety of individuals living or
working in this area of the community.
Significant utility extensions will be
required and those extensions will be
the responsibility of the entity
developing the land.
Certified mailing was sent to all land
owners and utilities within the annexed
area not less than 20 business days
prior to the public hearing. According
to the calendar, 20 business days prior
to today's hearing was May 12th and the
certified mailing was sent on May 7th.
The earliest confirmed receipt was May
11th and property owners within 300 ft
of the subject property were also mailed
notice during that time period. This
annexation is accompanied by an assigned
zoning. It is also accompanied by a
future land use map amendment and it is
also accompanied by an applicant
requested zone change on tonight's
agenda. All for introduction.
With that I am available for any
question.
>> Questions for staff. Mr. Moody.
>> Yeah. Thank you Mr. Mayor through you.
Uh thank you Mr. White. Um can you just
uh let the public know what was the uh
recommendation from the Cheyenne
planning commission please?
>> Mayor through you. So for the annexation
annexations do not go to the planning
commission. So there was no discussion
on the annexation. The items that went
to planning commission were the assigned
zoning the future land use map amendment
and the zoning map amendment.
>> Thank you Paul.
>> Yep.
>> Thank thank you. Uh thank you. Uh what
was what was their recommendation for
those uh zoning aspects?
>> Point of order.
>> Not your name to the item.
>> I agree.
Anybody else?
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. I am uh wondering
if you can tell us if you have heard
from anyone regarding this um
annexation.
>> What kind of communications have you
had, Mr.
>> Uh Mayor? Through you. Um so
specifically for this, there have been
no communications um for the annexation
itself. So there's been no public
comment or anything on the annexation.
>> Mr. Leborn, sir.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Uh Mr. White, I
believe you mentioned the uh mapping
question.
Um are you referring to the action that
occurred at the planning commission or
the I believe they were making a
recommendation about the map. So your
your reference is to the existing map,
not any change in that.
Mr. White,
>> mayor through you. So at planning
commission, they discussed the assigned
zoning, the future land use map
amendment, and the applicant requested
zoning map amendment. So those were the
items that were discussed at planning
commission. The annexation itself of the
3,459.99
acres was not discussed at planning
commission.
[clears throat]
>> Yes, I think we're all aware of that.
Thank you,
>> Mr. Wolf. Uh Thank you, mayor. Through
you, um,
Mr. White, um,
how many times did you meet with
Microsoft uh, to discuss this
annexation?
>> Mayor Thu, I have not met with Microsoft
specifically on this. if they've met
with others in my department. Um, we had
one pre-application meeting that was
with AVI for prior to submittal of the
application, but there hasn't been a
direct meeting that I have been a part
of when it's come to meeting with
Microsoft for this annexation.
>> So, Mr. Mayor, follow up, please. Thank
you. Um, so Mr. Bloom might have met
with Microsoft or uh Mr. Lloyd,
>> you want to ask a question?
>> I did. [laughter]
Do you know whether Mr. Bloom or Mr.
Lloyd met with Microsoft?
>> Mayor Thu, I'm not aware if they have or
haven't.
>> As a point of order, is this related to
the annexation council?
>> Absolutely. Councilwoman Aldridge.
>> Mr. Bloom, do you want to answer the
question?
>> Mayor, members of the council, Charles
Bloom, planning and development
director. Um, we had one pre-application
meeting that I was aware of that staff
had attended with this. There were
consultants on board. I do not know the
specifics as to if there's a Microsoft
representative on board or if anyone was
identified as Microsoft on that that
call. It was through consultants. I do
not attend most pre-application meetings
and I have not met with Microsoft on
this parcel whatsoever.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, thank you. Followup, Mr.
Bloom. um
in in the the paniply of annexations
that you have been involved with where
does this rank in terms of the number of
acres involved
>> Mr.
Mayor through members of the council
Charles BL development director. Um this
probably is one of the larger
annexations that I have seen here in the
city of Cheyenne.
>> Sweet grass
>> mayor threw you the council. Sweetgrass
was another large one. Uh that one I'm
not that predated me by just a little
bit. Um High Plains annexation which was
to the south for the Bison Business
Park. That was a large one as well. I
believe this one would comfortably take
the lead, but it's hard to know without
looking at exact acreages.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> thank you, Mr. Mayor. So when you get a
a gigantic annexation proposed like
that, does it trigger any additional
thinking processes,
uh,
data
requests, anything special when you're
talking about annexing 3,500 acres of
land?
>> Mr. Bloom,
>> mayor, three, the members of the council
and Councilman Wolf. Um, not
necessarily. I mean it does it does
bring up the question of well this area
will need to have city services and the
developer will ultimately have to
provide those public services. Um this
is again an applicant initiated one. So
we look at it as being a project that
they are comfortable in providing those
services. Um our primary concern is is
to look at that annexation area and to
see if it's feasible um if it's adjacent
um if it can be served by public
utilities. In this case, it does check
off all those boxes.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um do you talk
with the developer Microsoft about what
their plans are for developing this uh
proposed an annex land?
>> Mr. Mayor through to council and council
member Wolf. Um we we do chat with um
developers on what their potential plans
are um if they do choose to disclose
those. And this one we do understand was
for a uh data center campus. That was
sort of what had been discussed through
some of the um meetings as this this was
filed but um we don't get into
specifics.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Well, I mean, did you did it occur to
you that, you know, you might have
talked to them about say, why don't you
just annex now a part of this like 200
acres, 300 acres, and then when
Microsoft actually begins to develop
this, which may be years from now, that
you'd consider or the council then would
consider uh annexing the rest of it.
Mr. Boom, I don't know if you want to
answer that question or not, sir.
>> Mayor, members of the council to
Councilman Wolf, um we typically don't
ask people that are willing and signing
a petition to annex to reduce annexation
size. Um, we let that decision be upon
them as to what they feel comfortable
with the annexation because we do not
know what any specifics of any uh any
project details are or what their uh
real estate um how that deal may look
with the people they're purchasing the
land from. We hope leave it at the
discretion of them as to what area they
wish to annex.
>> Mr. Mayor, um followup, please.
>> Mr.
Um you're intimately involved uh in um
trying to start the process to do an
update to the 12-year outofdate uh uh
plan Cheyenne, aren't you?
>> Sir, mayor through you to members of the
council and Councilman Wolf. Um yes, we
are beginning the update to the
comprehensive plan. It is the last land
use element for our comprehensive plan
was addressed in 2014. Comprehensive
plans typically have a shelf life that
are looking for projecting future future
scenarios for 20 to 30 years. So it is
well within the time frame being
relevant. However, we have had so many
different changes in the community that
it does warrant a relook. Um in looking
at the proposals we recently received uh
which were uh plenty we received plenty
of complete proposals. Um, we did see a
lot of examples of other comprehensive
plans that were created for other
communities u nationwide, regionally and
even nationwide. And those uh plans, a
lot of them were updating plans that
were 10, 15, 20 years old as well. So,
we kind of are following uh the path of
how most plans are funded by
municipalities um because they typically
do have a you should be refreshing them
every 5 years, at least the core
principles of them. Um, but they usually
uh seem to be updated every about 10 to
15 years or right in the middle of that.
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> followup.
>> Um, and believe me, I'm not criticizing
you. In fact, I applaud that that you're
starting this work. But as you looked at
this giant annexation and as you looked
at all of the hull about that we
have faced as a city council and your
office has faced, did did it occur you
all to think maybe maybe this annexation
could proceed in a couple steps, but
maybe it might even be better off to
just be considered in in the future,
two, three years from now when you've in
fact updated plan Cheyenne.
>> Mr. Wolf, I think I can answer that
question. And that is that's not our
staff's position to tell people when
it's appropriate for them to bring a
piece of property. The uh state law says
that if they bring a petition to us, we
must look at that petition and if it
meets the criteria shall by ordinance
annex that property. And so it I I don't
know that it's staff's position to u to
censor applications. That's our job.
Well, Mr. Mayor, just to
>> Would you not agree with that, sir?
>> No, I don't agree with that. Actually,
>> I think our staff should be able to tell
people when they um when they should be
able to bring an annexation that that
they're not elected officials. We're the
elected officials. That's our job,
>> Mr. Mayor. And and in fact, I've had
this discussion with you and I agree.
It's your job.
>> Yeah. It's your job to take a look at
something of this magnitude and make a
judgment about whether or not it ought
to proceed through our regular processes
or in fact we might think hard about an
annexation of this size for a for a
topic of this controversy and treat it
in some different kind of manner. That's
my point. And but to the question about
plan Cheyenne, we have this planning
process that we're starting right now
and that will take a considerable amount
of time. But if Microsoft isn't going to
develop this property for years, why
don't we include
this annexation or a part of this
annexation into the depths of that
planning process instead of just saying,
you know, we got to take it on in the
same way. And look at the absolute irony
of what we're doing, which is we treat a
2.7 acre annexation with the same
processes that we treat 3500.
>> Mr. Wolf, I I think if you were to poll
your colleagues here and say that I have
the authority to decide what comes
before this governing body, I think
you'd lose probably 8 to1 in that uh in
that vote. Um, you know, I I think the
uh the job is we're separate but equal
and when those applications come, we're
part of the all of us together are the
legislative body of uh of the governing
body and it should be done as a joint
decision. Um, if you want to delegate
that to me, I'm happy to do that, but I
think your colleagues would would
disagree with you, sir.
Um,
well, it's an interesting discussion,
mayor, and um, frankly, looking at
today's agenda, I'm not sure I would
disagree with I'd love to actually
delegate to you and to the city clerk
and to the president a lot more
authority over our agenda. Um, but
that's a separate topic. But, but my
point is and my question to uh, Mr.
Bloom and I'm going to ask same
questions of Microsoft which are
something of this magnitude
is something that we ought to give lots
more careful thought to. Mr. Wolf, I
think we're conflating the the
development action with with uh
annexation. Annexation doesn't do
anything but change the color of the
map. What you're concerned about is what
happens once it's annexed. And uh that
is another process the governing body
goes through and that is when we do the
zoning for it, when we do the final plat
for it, uh when we do those types of
actions, but you know, if we were to
just annex this property and it sits
there for a decade or so, it doesn't
really change anything, does it?
Honestly,
>> well, it it may well it may well change
and and in 10 years a heck of a lot of
things may change. And and I take some
guidance
from what our good governor just said to
us last week, which is in his executive
order on data centers. You know, he says
local authority and community investment
were keeping power close to
>> point of order. Are we on annexation or
are we on data centers?
>> Good question.
>> Madame Councilwoman, you cannot possibly
separate them today. These are separate
actions.
>> It doesn't matter whe they're the
separate actions. It's all combined.
>> Mr. Wolf, I don't agree. We're all we're
really doing today is changing the color
of the map from being in the county to
being in the city, and nothing else is
being done at this point. I I appreciate
you have a different view, but I don't
agree.
>> Well, Mr. Mayor, and I've had this
discussion with you, sir. What I'm
trying to do is encourage you to do
exactly what the governor says, which is
city councils while encouraging
developers to invest in local housing,
charity, and infrastructure. And this is
the moment to be thinking about that.
This is the time between now and the
finalization of this annexation, zoning,
map change, they're all one. It's one
giant ball. And we shouldn't kid
ourselves that we are in fact looking at
just the annexation because this is the
time for this council, for this
government, for Mr. Bloom to actually
take a hold of these issues and make
them reality.
>> Mr. Wolf, we have had this discussion
and you know I I think uh doing a
community benefit requirement or asking
them to uh do things in order to be
annexed you know again feels like almost
like extortion to me and I don't I just
don't agree at this point in time what
we're doing is annexing a piece of
property. If in fact the companies want
to do some things like we have later on
in our agenda um I think that's well
welcomed but um to condition annexation
on that I think is a slippery slope sir.
>> And Mr. Mayor. Um, it it's not a
slippery slope. It's in fact the the
slope that that we are on right now.
It's not extortion. I'm talking about
something that I'm going to call a
mutually
beneficial partnership agreement with
Microsoft
>> which means you can be annexed if you
give us what a rec center or something
like that.
>> No. No. My proposal is going to be 3% of
the total cost of the project.
>> Oh god.
two rec centers. Okay.
>> Two rec centers, right? Yeah.
>> Sir, I just I I just don't agree. Thank
you. Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Yes, sir.
>> For our staff, right?
>> Yes.
>> Michelle, I'm keeping Dr. Alders. I
apologize.
>> That's okay. Mayor Collins for you. I am
curious about um whether statute uh
Wyoming state statute requires has any
minimal or maximum land acreage or size
um for annexation and uh any uh
specialized considerations based on
size.
>> Mr. Bloom,
>> mayor, members of council, there is no
size limitation, minimum or maximum with
annexation.
>> Mr. Mr. Bloom, would you say that it's
important for us to have a um a
regulatory process that is consistent
when people come to us? I mean, that's
what we're trying to do, right? We're
trying to treat all the annexations
similarly so that developers when they
come to us know what our process is.
>> Mayor, three to members of the council,
that is correct. And I just like to
remind everyone this is an applicant
petition. Once they sign the
application, they cannot withdraw that
annexation petition. One of the benefits
of that is once this is annexed,
regardless of if the zoning is
established that they wish, the land use
is established as they wish, it is under
our jurisdiction and subject to our
rules and regulations. We sat for um
just over 40 years with land north of
Frontier Mall. That was an island and we
were lucky that that stayed in the same
family and eventually it was annexed and
it's agreeable with the land use plan to
develop. There's a real risk there that
that was not annexed in the past. it
could have developed in any way we we
would have seen. We've seen other areas
of the community where we've extended
urban services, water, sewer, and that
area has not been annexed and that is
annexed outside of our jurisdiction,
outside of our regulations. And there's
a couple of different stories that you
can look at how things have annexed. Um,
so it is important to bring this in and
again this is a landowner initiated
annexation. Their petition cannot be
withdrawn unless there's consent from
the governing body. Understood. Dr.
Emmens, we'll start with you and go to
Mr. Moody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. So, um, Mr. Bloom,
have you said this is an owner initiated
annexation request, correct,
>> Mr. Bloom?
>> Mayor to to council member Emmens. Yes,
that is correct.
>> Um, followup.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Has the uh landowner done met all the
requirements for annexation?
>> Mayor Mr. Mayor you members of council,
Dr. Emmens. Yes, they have.
>> Have we done our I'm sorry.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Have we done our due diligence on our
part for annexation,
>> Mr. Moon?
>> Mayor, through you to me council and Dr.
Emmens. Yes.
>> One more.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Is there any reason not to approve that
you found in your due diligence,
>> Mayor members of the council, and Dr.
Ammons? No, there's no reason to not
approve the annexation. So each one of
us can vote against this if we choose
when when the time is right. Correct.
>> Dr. Emmens. Yes. That's an individual um
decision we'll have to make based on the
evidence.
>> Okay. Thank you,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Question.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Three. Uh thank
you, Mr. Bloom. Were any of the
residents in um Sweetestrass
neighborhood notified especially in the
southern part?
>> Mr. Bloom, are any of them within 300
ft? mayor through you, members of
council and and councilman Moody likely
not through direct mailed notice because
they are not within 300 feet. Um there
was published notice um that was put out
in the newspaper.
>> Do you have a topographical map that
shows the uh the ridge that runs between
the the two
>> mayor members of council? We do have a
topographical map that we could
pull up. It's on our GIS. This aerial
this aerial does a very good job of
detailing it. You can see the ridge line
that runs north westerly of this
property. Um that ridge line uh is the
high point. Uh this development area uh
falls off the ridge line I believe about
about 10 to 20 feet as it keeps on
heading down as you head south.
>> Thank you, Mr. Bloom. Mr. Moody,
>> Dr. You have another question, ma'am.
>> Oh, no.
>> Okay.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Mayor Collins for you. I'm wondering uh
if when we have met when the petitioner
has met all of the requirements, we've
done our due diligence, is there any um
precedent in case law um about
um denying this type of an annexation
and any liability um or litigation that
has pursued from situations like that?
>> Mr. Mr. Bloom, do you uh know that
answer?
>> Mayor, members of the council, I'm I'm
not in the third floor legal office, so
I don't know if I can actually answer
that for Mr. Holiday Express
>> signing up
uh recently. Yes, actually. But um I'm
not a I'll pass that on to Mr. Hopkins
if he has an answer.
>> David, do you have any?
>> Um [clears throat]
uh Mr. Mayor, um Dr. Aldrich the really
what the what the council is looking at
is whether the elements have been met in
within that annexation statute if you
believe that those elephants elements
elements
have been met um then the statute says
the city council should approve the
annexation. So it's really more a
question of do you believe that the
those individual elements that are
discussed as part of uh what staff has
presented are they really met or not?
That's the where the real question
generally lies.
>> Mr. Bloom.
>> Mayor, if I just may add, there there is
a
relevant planning case law that's based
on decisions. If an application meets
the review criteria
um and a governing body arbitrarily
denies that application,
uh the applicant would have the right to
appeal that decision. Um I could not
predict how that would go in a court of
law, but there are a lot of cases I
understand that um if the applicant is
the application is denied for arbitrary
reasons that it could put us in a in a
bad situation.
>> Say arbitrary or capriccious reasons is
what the
>> mayor that's correct.
>> Thank you. All right. Anybody else? Mr.
Cray for staff.
>> Mr. Mayor, I just want to follow up. Did
did our uh attorney say that we shall
annex if we believe it met the
requirements or we can
>> 151402 says if it meets all the criteria
you shall by ordinance annex the
property the exact words.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. Actually uh Mr. Mayor
actually that citation is in 406.
>> Yep.
Um,
so no, it's in 404,
but but not to not to get we'll have
plenty of time over the next month to
get into the legal arguments about what
we as the council can and can't do with
this. Um, and what the legal standards
are because I I have been looking into
those. Um, so we'll spare the audience
that discussion today.
>> It'll be fun when we do. All right,
sounds like we're done with the council.
We'll go out to the audience to speak to
the uh in this public hearing for the
annexation of 3,4
59.99 acres. If I put my glasses on,
it's a lot easier to read. Jim, welcome.
Jim Cher, award one candidate. I
strongly oppose this annexation. I know
where you're going with the whole legal
end on it. But what really disappoints
me is that with these annexations,
especially with the data centers,
Microsoft, whoever it is, they always
sneak in with the state statute. Well,
as long as it's continuous, as long as
it's uh uh safety and water and all that
stuff there. It it goes beyond that. And
through you, Mayor, Mr. Wolf, I totally
respect your proactive thoughts on this.
You know, let's let's get the elephant
in the room before it gets too big. And
that affects a lot of those people.
Whether that's going to be ward one or
what ward that is, it still affects the
quality of life for the city of Cheyenne
residents with that large of an
annexation. So I would uh strongly
encourage this governing body not to go
and approve this annexation at this
time. Thank you,
>> Heather. Welcome tonight.
>> Thank you, Heather Madrid. Whoa. Um I
live in Harmony Meadows. Um, I actually
kind of have the same question of how it
makes sense. I mean, I know that Mr.
Bloom said that there are no um,
differences in the law about 2 acres
versus 3,500 acres. Um, but I wonder why
it's excusable to continually update
this outdated land use map because
there's no way that it could have
foreseen this kind of unprecedented
growth and scale. But it's not
appropriate then to also update the
regulations around annexation and
resoning etc etc. Um it just kind of
feels like you guys want it all your way
or you know it doesn't quite like it's
not the math isn't mathing as they say.
Um [clears throat] I also wonder how
this is protecting the health, safety
and welfare if people don't live there
yet. Um it's not really protecting
anybody. In fact, I would argue that
it's harmful to that area and to
this last gentleman's point. Um,
with this large of an annexation and
what we all know is going to be there,
it's going to affect the entire city,
not just people within 300 ft. Um,
and if there is no plan of what's going
to happen over the next 10 years, how is
it even possible that the criteria in
Wyoming statute 15-1-405
have been met if there is no there isn't
even a plan? The at the um planning
commission they were Microsoft was asked
how many buildings they didn't they
didn't know. So how is that how is it
even possible to say that that statute
has been met if there is no plan? It
just um I would ask that
all everything needs to be updated not
just the land use map so that so that
Microsoft can have it their way. Um,
everything should be updated and brought
to current, not not only what benefits
global corporate billionaires who are
trying to land grab in rural America.
Thank you,
>> Mr. Lloyd. Did you want to speak?
>> Mr. Mayor, Seth Lloyd at the City of
Shine Planning and Development
Department. Um, I'm probably the only
planner here in the office that was here
when we did the sweetgrass annexation.
Um, so I just wanted to shed some light
on that process that happened back in
that day. Um, we had a two annexations
that totaled over 3,000 acres with sweet
grass. Um, and they brought in the land
um, anticipating a 50-year buildout. So,
not all the land is going to be built
all at the same time. Um, and the main
reason they did it all at once is
because they wanted a unified
development program for the Sweet Grass
development. It's one giant PUB. They've
changed it a few times. You've changed
it probably within the last few months.
So, it it changes, yes, but they had a
long range plan. They wanted to kind of
get that going. And they had that
50-year buildout program. So, they
annexed all of that 3,000 acres. Um,
only 2,000 of which are really sweet
grass. There's another thousand that
approximately that it took to get to
Sweetgrass to annex it. But, they had
that long range plan. And when the city
staff at that day in that day reviewed
the program, um we had comments from
various city agencies and departments
saying this is how many more staff
members we're going to have to have in
order to take care of this land at full
buildout. We had comments I believe and
and I'd have to go back to staff report
to read them all, but I believe we had
them from public works and we had them
from police and we had them from fire
saying this is what it's going to take
to service this area with that
annexation. And admittedly, that
development program was a lot more dense
than this is anticipated to be. um the
single family homes, commercial
development, streets, roads, very very
dense development. So it was would be a
higher impact upon city services at full
buildout, but that we had that greater
standard of review on that larger
annexation than we did with say someone
annexing single family home to connect
to sewer. Um so I just want to shed
light on what has happened in the past.
Um uh and we've we've had a similar but
not exactly the same because it's a
different development program but a
similar type of annexation historically.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. M
>> sir, did you want to speak?
>> Sir, did you want to speak?
>> Please come forward.
>> Could you do me a favor and bring that
microphone up so we can hear you and
give us your name?
>> Uh Brandt Miller.
>> Welcome. I'm on the Larmy County
Groundwater Control Board and um just
kind of concerned about how the water's
where the water's going to come from,
how it's going to be used. If it's all
coming from, you know, of the city, then
is that going to affect the discharge
into Crow Creek? Because what comes down
Crow Creek affects the groundwater and
Carpenter. I represent the Carpenter
area. So, just really urge you to think
about the water because we're already
having trouble with it. So,
Mr. Mill, I would, you know, I I guess
there's if it develops in the city,
it'll be on city water with city sewer.
If it's identified in the county, then
they'll be drilling wells into the the
aquifer.
>> Sure.
>> And I don't know if you have an opinion
on which way would be better for your
control district.
>> Right. Well, it would have to come
before us, but yeah, it's I just would,
you know, ask you to get a hold of the
state engineer and have him look at
what's going on. use the the state
engineers. So, I just want to, you know,
bring that to your attention because
we're really, you know, water's getting
hard to come by in Carpenter. So,
>> appreciate you being here this evening.
>> Here and runs that way and if you use it
before it gets to us, then gets kind of
rough. Yeah.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Thank you.
>> Hello, Miss Christensen.
>> Honorable mayor, members of the council,
my name is Mark Christensen. I am with
AVIPC. um agent for the applicant. Um so
this annexation is an owner initiated
annexation of approximately 3,459 acres
of land that is uh approximately 46%
contiguous to the city limits. The
current owner in Microsoft has
designated this as an area of expansion
for the Bison Business Park. In order to
continue evaluation of what can be done
on the property, the parties need to
know if we are going to be developing in
the city or in the county or pursuing
development in either of those places
and what zone they will be developing
under which is the impetus for the this
application. So once this is known, uh,
Microsoft will begin to complete the
transportation studies, the cultural
studies, environmental studies,
drainage, sound, power studies, and
water and sewer feasibility studies so
that we can prove to the reviewing
agencies that we meet all of the
required rules. Both parties after the
initial consultation uh with the
pre-lication meeting that was previously
mentioned uh determined that it was best
to pursue this initial development um
with the city uh before pursuing it with
the county. So this is why the
annexation is before you. So the first
step in the process is to evaluate the
design standards of the property and its
potential development. The land
currently borders Microsoft property,
the current land owners property, EOG
land, the state of Wyoming own land, and
then land planned for a solar farm.
There was an open house um for the
neighboring property owners and all of
the owners of the Grass Hill subdivision
to the southeast of the parcel. Uh only
three members of the public did attend
this meeting, but we were able to answer
many of their questions. Um the
Microsoft team might have some more
insights on some of those discussions.
Uh but we concur with the staff that
this meets the requirements of the
annexation as found in state statutes.
Um thank you for your time.
>> Thank you.
>> Hi ma'am.
>> Hello Rachel Irwing, land development
and permitting program manager for
Microsoft. Um good evening mayor,
members of the council, and members of
the public. Thank you again for your
time and consideration. Uh I wanted to
briefly address an important question
raised during the planning commission
last week as to why Highlands is being
proposed at this scale. Um and why an
area this large? Uh Highlands represents
both a near-term opportunity and a
long-term planning effort. Large
contiguous parcels with the
infrastructure characteristics needed
for future development are increasingly
rare. Um, planning comprehensively now
allows us to have growth occur
thoughtfully and with the city's input
and with the public's input over time
rather than incrementally um, and
reactively parcel by parcel.
Importantly, this does not mean that all
3,50 acres that Microsoft would own
would develop all at once or in the same
way. Complete and full buildout of the
site would likely be a 10 to 20 year
phased development. The larger planning
area provides flexibility to responsibly
coordinated infrastructure,
transportation, utilities, buffering,
environmental considerations, and future
community needs over many years and in
alignment with market demand and
infrastructure readiness. Microsoft has
already been a part of the community for
approximately 14 years. And our approach
has been and will continue to be to
consistently focus on long-term
partnership, infrastructure investment,
and responsible planning. Thank you for
your time and consideration.
>> Thanks for being here, Rachel.
Sir,
>> good evening, mayor, council members,
city staff, and members of the public.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak.
My name is Lucas Downey, and I work on
the community affairs team at Microsoft.
I'm new in this role, so for those that
I haven't met yet, it's a pleasure to be
here. And for those that I have, it's
great to see you again. While I may be
new in my role, Microsoft is not new to
Cheyenne. I want to reiterate the
statement about Microsoft operating here
for more than 14 years. We've called
Cheyenne home since 2012. And from the
start, we've tried to be good neighbors.
Not just a company with a footprint
here, but a partner invested in this
community's future.
That partnership starts with
transparency. On May 28th, we hosted an
open house that brought together more
than 150 community members, neighbors,
families, and local leaders to learn
about our plans, ask hard questions, and
share their concerns.
That conversation mattered to us, and we
intend to keep hosting events like this
throughout the summer. We want to keep
listening, keep showing up, and keep
addressing your feedback directly.
We've also tried to we've also tried to
back up our words with investment. Since
2018, Microsoft has supported 56
community projects across 28 local
organizations, and we've donated $4.7
million to local nonprofits and
organizations across Wyoming. That
includes partners many of you know. The
Boys and Girls Club of Cheyenne, LC, the
Wyoming Women's Business Center, Rooted
in Cheyenne, Habitat for Humanity, Kamya
Shelter, Climb Wyoming, and Cheyenne
Frontier Days, among more than 50 other
initiatives we're proud to stand behind.
And all this is anchored in our
community first commitments. They mean
five things. We pay the full cost of our
power so our data centers don't raise
your electricity bill. We minimize our
water use and we are committed to being
good stewards of the watershed.
We create local jobs. We invest in local
training and nonprofits and we
contribute to local taxes. In 2025,
Microsoft was the number one taxpayer in
the city of Cheyenne.
We know trust is earned, not announced.
We're committing to earning it this
summer and for years to come. And we're
not just proud of the 14 years we've
been a part of the community. We're
genuinely excited for the decades that
are still to come. Cheyenne isn't just
where we operate. It's where we intend
to keep growing, contributing, and
building in partnership with the
community. Thank you.
>> Thank you for being here, sir. Welcome.
>> You want to push that button? Yeah,
there you go.
>> Please identify yourself.
>> Hi, my name is Brian Napier. I'm a
Cheyenne resident since uh 2010. Uh and
that's why I'm here today. I wanted to
talk to you um about Microsoft being
here in our community because I've also
in addition to being a Wyoming resident,
I've also been a Microsoft employee
since 2016. And in my time with
Microsoft, you know, the we've been here
for I've been with Microsoft for 10
years and we've been uh everything I've
ever seen with the company has been
positive working with the community and
trying to be a good neighbor. And if I
didn't believe in that, I wouldn't be
standing in front of you here on their
behalf today. So, um I've started as a
logistics technician, which is an entry-
level role. I've managed to work my way
up through all the managerial ranks and
I'm now the IT operations manager and I
run this department with two other
individuals for our entire IT team.
We've hired a hundred people in the last
three years. We're bringing good jobs to
this community bringing great benefits
benefits that actually have given me my
family. Microsoft,
>> Mr. Mayor, what does this have to do
with the annexation? Second,
>> please continue, sir.
>> Yeah, I'm I'm a taxpayer. I just want to
say my piece. Thank you. Um,
can I about 10 seconds back on that?
>> I got you.
>> Thank you.
>> Microsoft has paid for my IVF through my
family and they we're going to be uh
good family planners for the rest of the
community. They have brought in many
jobs here, paid a lot of tax and
provided quality of life for many of our
teams. I I don't even want to talk to
you'all anymore. Thank you.
Good evening, Mr. Mayor and city
councilors, on the annexation that's
proposed here for the Highlands. Earlier
today, I sent you this map. Oh, sorry,
Betsy Hail, CEO of Cheyenne Leads. Uh
earlier today, I sent all of the council
members uh this map. And the reason that
I sent this map is I wanted to uh make
sure that not only you but also the
citizens and the community knew um the
adjacent land uses that this site uh is
adjacent to. And you can see from this
map that to the north of the proposed
annexation, you have the gravel pits. To
the east of the annexation, you have
5,000 acres of EOG uh resources, oil and
gas fracking wells. To the southeast of
the project, you'll have a 800 megawatt
900 megawatt solar farm that has been
approved by the county with Enbridge. Uh
also south, you'll see some state lands
and then on the uh southwest side you
see the Bison Business Park. In
conversations with the property owners,
uh you'll see that there's going to be a
planned conservation easement along the
bluffs uh clear up to the gravel pits.
And I wanted to make sure that you did
understand some of the elevation changes
that are out here. Uh when you get
toward the Sweetg Grass site, you'll see
that their elevation at the farthest
corner uh closest to Highlands is about
6,000
um 80 feet uh in elevation. Uh the
bluffs actually go up as high as 6,100
ft. So there is an incline there with
the bluffs. Then as you come into the
Highlands property itself, there's
actually a decline in elevation. So
you'll see it go back down into around
6,080 ft in through here. The land does
swing up again as you get down towards
the state land. It's about 6,200 feet in
elevation. And uh in the meeting uh that
we had with this county subdivision
that's down here uh next to the state
lands just east, uh we had some really
good conversations about that. The
lowest point in that subdivision is
right along the Cowboy Solar um property
and that's at 6,080 feet as well. And so
there is quite a bowl out there. I do
think there is something to be said for
economies of scale if you really do want
to do a development agreement of some
type that gives big impact. I think the
larger that the property is, the ability
to work within the community is much
easier rather than just more of a
patchwork approach. So I would encourage
you to do the annexation in total. Thank
you,
>> Betsy.
Mr. Mayor,
my apologies.
>> Go ahead, Mr. Wolf.
>> Mr. Mayor, first of all, the gentleman
standing behind you. I apologize. I was
not at all trying to be rude to you.
What you've jumped into is the middle of
a debate between all of us here over the
scope of what we're talking about
tonight.
>> Oh, I can understand. But I was getting
I was trying to wrap my point up which
was all coming around the bend before I
was cut off.
>> And I I I'm
>> sorry and I accept that.
>> Very sorry.
>> I accept that. That's okay
>> because we're in a bit of an argument
amongst ourselves. I understand you're
kind of in the middle of it. Um and but
it's it has nothing to do at all.
Please, we have tremendous respect for
you and for Microsoft and um and and
this process and um so thank you. Thank
you for taking your time. Thank you for
working on these things and and please
I'm I'm I'm sorry.
>> Yes, I do accept your apology. That's
okay. I know we're in a it's it's a it's
a weird spot we're in right now, but the
main point I wanted to get across here
is the idea behind the annexation is
we're going to do a lot of good for the
people in this community. It brings good
jobs, brings amazing healthcare, and
it's uh it's not something we get
everywhere. This is something that is
not something that people get an
opportunity to get more than once or
twice in their lifetime. Maybe we're
going to be bringing hundreds of jobs
for people to have this opportunity in
their lives to take care of their
families.
>> I have two children that I wouldn't have
had otherwise.
>> Not not not one kid. They've paid
Microsoft has paid for my entire IVF
process. I don't know anyone that's ever
gone through that, but you get the
option of maybe having $200,000 of debt
or a family. and they paid for my entire
stint. So that's that is what Microsoft
brings to the table here. You should
absolutely things because and the land
I'm sorry because it's going to give
people an opportunity to have a a
tremendous life and that's what it's
brought to me from the bottom to where I
am now. So thank you.
>> Thank you for coming back.
>> Thank you Betsy.
>> Thank you Mr. Mayor. Councelor Wolf.
Um,
Miss Hails,
um,
we just got your hand out, which has now
become in my mind the sort of 10, five,
nine
>> handout.
Um, and let me just ask you a couple
questions about that. I guess the first
one is as I understand it that
what you're counting in that is
buildings
is that right
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor through you know sir that
is not correct. So how a data center is
not a data center is not a data center
and I apologize if I haven't uh prefaced
how we count we actually count locations
addresses because if if you have a
Microsoft project you'll see something
like data halls right and they're built
in phases and over time if you work with
meta it's a much larger building. So if
we were to try to say it's the number of
buildings, uh we have some other data
centers in town that are a building with
four different data centers in them. So
it's very hard to come up with a what
would I call it? A metric, if you will,
of you know, if if something is a
100,000 square feet versus if something
is 800,000 square feet, is a building a
building? And so by going to an address
um uh or a campus if you will um or a
location then we feel like we can say
these are the locations where the data
centers are and that s is how we got to
the 10 uh that are operating and that
includes everything from the cogent uh
facility which is right across uh the
vioaduct on central uh to the echoar
data center that is associated with the
um satellite uplink facility. there. Uh
we also have we include the crypto uh
miners in that as well. Um and so when
you when you count to 10, you're
counting Microsoft locations. We have
Microsoft locations at Northrange a
location. Cheyenne Business Parkway, we
have a location. Bison Business Park, we
have a location. So wanting to make sure
that we're not saying, okay, over here
we have six buildings, but there's only
one building on the Meta campus. So, do
you count six data halls as data centers
or do you count that location because
they're all on one property as a data
center just as you would Meta. So,
that's where we're going with that. Uh,
we spent a lot of time with Black Hills
Energy and the Board of Public
Utilities. I mean, you could go to Taps
if you wanted to go to Taps. Taps would
make it sound incredibly large. So, um,
that's where we went, sir. I hope that
helps.
>> Oh, Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. What are you
talking about? Caps.
>> Taps. Water taps.
>> Water taps.
>> I'm sorry. I'm sorry. Little bit of dry
mouth here. Yeah.
>> Um All right. Well, Mr. Mayor, if I
might follow up. Um, so let's take the
Lumnavi building. Um,
>> is is that have to do with the
annexation? Mr. It it has absolutely to
do with these annexation because this is
all part of how we assess data centers
and this is all part of what Cheyenne
Leads has been trying to tell the
community about which is how many data
centers are there and there are not
surprisingly a number of ways to figure
those and I want to know how leads has
done it because you can't in fact
replicate their m
>> Mr. Wolf. Honestly, your council doesn't
agree. We're here to talk about an
annexation. If we want to talk about
data centers, there may be another more
appropriate place, but I just don't
think this is the time.
>> Mr. Mayor, you've allowed several people
to come in here and talk about data
centers already.
>> You know, I give a little grace to
people who aren't part of the data uh
part of the governing body, but for us,
we have to be held to a higher standard.
Don't you agree? Oh, I intend to high
hold us all to a high standard,
including Miss Hails because she hasn't
explained and isn't able to explain yet
how this
10, five, nine actually is determined.
>> What I heard her say is that we have 10
campuses where data centers are located,
five that are under construction, and
nine that are in some sort of a planning
stage.
>> Okay, let me ask you one more question,
Mr. Mayor. Okay. So, how do you compare
Lumnavi at 45,000 square feet and Meta
at 715,000 square feet?
>> Mr. Mayor, through you. Exactly. And
that if if you could come up with that,
councelor Wolf, that would be great. Um,
it is not something that has been done
anywhere well in the country because of
this very different a data center is a
data center is a data center. We could
certainly say how many square feet of
data centers there are. Um I'm not sure
that would be as meaningful to people.
You know, the Lowe's distribution center
is the largest building in Wyoming and
it's a million square feet. So it's not
a data center at all, but it's a very
large building. And so if you can come
up with and maybe perhaps we can work
with the city and the county planners
and we can try to see if there is some
uniform form of measurement. Uh we could
certainly work on that.
>> I thought of one more Mr. Mayor. Well,
in fact, guess what? I asked AI to do
that for me.
And they actually came up with a formula
which is most heavily weighted towards
the actual power usage of the plants
themselves. And they basically rank
the if you if you assign a metric to the
smallest one, the smallest power.
>> Point of order. Mr. Mayor, we're we're
talking about annexation here, not the
size of data centers.
>> Okay, Mr. M Mr. Mayor, let me let me
just do this as I do it in a courtroom,
which is may I make an offer of proof?
>> Can I say objection, your honor?
>> Uh, no, no, you've already the Mr. Wolf,
actually, I agree. You know, I think
there's going to be a better time and
place to have this discussion. We're
having a public hearing to talk about
this. We give a little grace to the
folks in the audience because they don't
know our processes, but I think as
members of the governing body, we should
know them better.
>> Yeah. Can I make just one more point
then? The final point is this that if
you use other standards then you have to
consider the meta under this power
standard to be 30 data centers. You have
to consider tall grass to be 320
data centers. And so
>> the point is made Mr. Well, thank you.
>> The point is
>> your point is made. Thank you.
>> All right.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Thank you,
Councelor Wolf.
>> Mr. Mayor, just for clarification, just
wanted everybody to know this is a
public hearing, so no vote on this is
going to be taken tonight. It gets
referred to committee. I think it's
important that folks remember that as
well.
>> I mean, the purpose of what we're here
tonight is to talk about the statutory
criteria, uh, to put on the record what
those criteria are so that we can make a
good decision when it comes to the
annexation itself.
>> Mr. Swain.
>> Uh, good evening, mayor, members of the
council. Brandon Swain, W3. Uh, just a
few comments on some of the discussion
within the governing body earlier. I
don't know that there's a minimum
standard for annexation, but I have
owner initiated uh as little as onethird
of an acre. Um, at times as a private
developer, and I won't hold you in
suspense. I'm I support any annexation
that meets the requirements that's owner
initiated. Um, uh, I think one of the
strengths of the planning department,
even though sometimes it could be
painful as a developer, is consistency
and and a clinical attitude. I've never
had a time uh where anyone in the
planning department has opined uh or
told me to slow things down or if
anything to ramp it up. I think their
job is to simply enforce the unifi
excuse me unified development code. They
are the planning and development
department. So I would assume their
disposition is to try and give projects
a path forward. Uh I've had some extreme
scenarios whether it's hey what about a
nine-story building in Holiday Park and
I purchase city land or maybe I'll
propose a fuel station at Story and
Marshall. I'm not sure. Um, but the
planning department generally is going
to give you just a simple clinical
response. And I think that that's a good
thing. At times it can be painful as a
developer when you're not agreeable to
what some of the standards are, but I
think generally for the public, it's
good that someone annexing as little as
a third of an acre or nearly 3,600,
changing zoning on one parcel or a
thousand is a consistent process. And
and I really feel for that department.
It's not as if they have 20 staff. It's
a very limited amount of folks that are
doing some heavy lifting. So, I just
wanted to offer some comments to
hopefully paint a different narrative
that they're arbitrary in some of their
enforcement of code. I found them to be
very fair and consistent. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Brandon. Jim, you've already
spoken. We'll see if anybody else has
not had a chance to do that yet. Anybody
else online or
Go ahead, Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Mr. Miller, welcome.
Hello. Can you hear me?
>> Yes, Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> Oh, great. Sorry, I uh I actually joined
this meeting a little bit late today. Um
so I apologize. I've just come into it
now, but it looks like we are discussing
or not discussing the annexation of uh
Microsoft. Uh the is that correct? What
we're doing is having a public hearing
to talk about whether the conditions for
annexation are met for the uh Microsoft
uh annexation of 3,459 acres.
>> Okay. Okay. And so I suppose that the
floor has kind of been opened up for uh
general discussion uh for and against
the annexation in regards to how data
centers are going to impact that and
everything. Is that correct?
>> No, I don't think so. I think we're
talking about the conditions for just it
seems like Mr. Wolf and and M Miss Hails
was were just talking about data centers
and so I assume that uh it's about data
centers. I'm going to go ahead and uh
just jump on now. Mayor Collins, members
of the city council for the permanent
administrative record, uh Charles
Miller, I'm issuing a formal
constructive notice tonight regarding
the proposed hypers scale data center
expansions uh specifically neutralizing
the rhetorical alibis presented by
Cheyenne Leadeds and Microsoft um during
the June 1 uh planning commission
session. Uh this governing body is being
asked to authorize multi,000 acre
industrial zoning while operating in an
absolute state of information blindness.
First, regarding the administrative
shield
>> offered by Betsy Hale stood on the
public record and attempting to discuss
this city
>> by assuring us that the environmental
and aesthetic impacts of these mega
campuses will be strictly regulated by
private conditions cover Mr. Miller, I
have to agree with the council. You're
talking about things that aren't before
us right now. What's before us is
whether the 3,459 acres meet the
criteria for being annexed. Um,
>> so do you want to get on to that topic?
I'm happy to listen to it.
>> Um, okay. So,
so are you trying to split up the fact
that you guys are trying to change this
over to uh a different um zoning or
>> I mean that that that'll be on first
reading later on in this meeting and
will be talked about in the next few
weeks, but it's not on the it's not what
we're on this time.
>> Okay. Okay. How about this one? Um so
the uh due to FIN fce's March 2025 roll
back of the corporate transparency act
uh and this this ties in because uh as
far as the annexation is concerned
uh Betsy Hail is indicating uh that the
um the environmental and aesthetic
impacts of these mega campuses will be
strictly regulated by private conditions
covenants.
>> I apologize but your time is up sir.
Thank you.
Anybody else online?
Jim, please.
>> Jim Cherro, board one candidate. Just to
recoup my time, I'm not going to take a
long time on it. Just as staff had said
when you did with the subdivision that
you did a little bit more due diligence
on that, you did a little bit more
research on that. I'm asking that you go
and do that before going and send this
over to the planning committee. Again, I
I highly encourage you not to go to
improve this for quality of life.
Technology is going to go and change. I
remember when, you know, we used to be
on dialup with AOL on that. And then
what's going to happen? We're going to
have all these data centers. We're going
to have we're going to have a ghost town
of warehouses and buildings and that.
Not to mention if I win the lottery and
I wanted to put a steel mill in here,
but if I go and donate to the Boys and
Girls Club or I go and put in a new rec
center or, you know, CFD or that, that
makes me a good steward. No, we got to
look at the quality of life and not look
at that mighty buck on this. So, please
take your time on this like you did with
the subdivision. I'm I'm all I'm all for
it for, you know, if it was for a
subdivision. That's quality of life.
You're getting affordable housing for
folks, not doing 3,400 acres. If they
want to buy some land, I'll sell them my
40 acres out of Medicine Bow. They'd
love to have employment out there.
That's it. Your mayor. Thank you.
>> All right. We're still on the uh public
hearing to talk about the annexation. Is
there anybody else in the audience that
wants to speak on this public hearing
either online or in public or in pro
person? There I go.
Nobody else. All right, we're going to
close that public hearing and open it up
to the governing body. Uh, anybody on
the governing body? Mr. White, did you
want to speak? Sir,
>> I was just going to ask our city
attorney,
what is a formal constructive notice?
>> We we've been getting that a lot
recently. So, from the same person. So,
is that a legal term or what is it?
>> Should we ask Chad GPT?
I should have done that actually, but I
didn't.
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor, Councilman White,
as far as the city's proceedings go, it
doesn't really mean anything.
>> That's what I thought. Thank you.
>> Anybody else from the governing body?
All right. Hearing none, the purpose of
the public hearing. Oh,
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Thank you, [snorts] Mr. Mayor.
Um obviously [clears throat]
this is um
a big big
issue
and in the map we just got handed
you can see that it deals with a number
of adjacent or nearby issues
that uh
possibly not being taken in
consideration tonight
but that are part of the community's
interest and certainly um something that
I'm very interested in.
One of the things I'd like to point out
here is this narrow focus that we have
and we've had tonight
about point of order and what's
appropriate to discuss. And one of the
things I'd like to point out, Mr. mayor
is the five hours I recently spent here
with the planning commission in regard
to uh this overall effort
and I I believe that that's germanine to
the discussion. I think it's important
that we look at the fact that most of
the our guests here from Microsoft were
here for that meeting and they discussed
what they were talking about and it was
about the map and about the zoning that
will occur.
And Mr. Mayor and [clears throat]
members of the council, I just got to
say how proud I was of our planning
commission.
They really really did their best and
you can imagine and it certainly is that
is equally applicable to us.
We don't make decisions like this.
Haven't before. [clears throat]
Certainly not in a such a politically
charged atmosphere with so many nearby
aspects.
And I don't think we can look at this in
that narrow view that's been suggested
tonight that we're changing the color on
the map.
Mr. Mayor, we're not changing the color
on the map. We are adopting the rules
and regulations of the city.
That's a really serious thing.
And I want to emphasize as well that
certainly leads and the many projects
that have been developed uh that I'm
aware of have really benefited this city
in many ways that uh the efforts with
Microsoft to this point have um
certainly not occurred in this type of
an atmosphere.
But one of the things that con that I'm
considering to [clears throat] be
serious, Mr. Mayor, is I can't get the
minutes of that planning commission
meeting
that just happened. Five hours
good discussion
use of the people that sit on the
planning commission. And they wanted to
understand
uh as they do uh these other annexations
big little they wanted to apply their
knowledge to that and I think they did
and it was uh certainly interesting
but when we don't have the minutes
we don't have a real chance to discuss
the action that they took
and they took several votes. I I
personally uh [snorts] don't want to
call on my recollection. I think we need
to go to the record and I think that
that's a very important part of this and
certainly those uh those minutes can be
uh dispersed as draft minutes. Don't
have to wait a month for them to be uh
approved by the next meeting of the
commission. So, there's got to be some
middle ground on this.
Um, I'm not hearing a lot of it,
but this is something we need to discuss
and look at. And I think certainly from
my perspective, and I will be having a
vote on that annexation action,
we need to consider South Cheyenne
that's immediately adjacent here,
and all the needs and changes that are
going on there.
because of this project as well as
others. And I believe that there's
contributions that should be considered
to help that neighborhood as well as
other issues here in the city. And I
would point out, Mr. mayor and members
of the council that on our map and I was
glad to have it pointed out by staff
here, the sweetgrass annexation came
with an annexation agreement
and it was one that we've modified as
was pointed out,
but it wasn't a blanket
approach to um what the property owners
and interestingly enough they happen to
be the same property owners. I don't
believe that uh Microsoft has yet
purchased the Highlands property, but uh
certainly the Lumis family is well
known. So I think there are some options
here we should be considering
and some thoughts that need to be made
and that we really
should be careful
about allowing broad discussion.
This isn't a narrow
uh issue of changing a color on a map.
This is the future of our city in a very
very complex
relationship
and I certainly look forward to
continued discussion with uh some of the
people that have spoken here. I
appreciated the meeting that I went to
at the college. Um I went to the meeting
at the uh civic center. There just a lot
of knowledge we need to get here and a
lot of fear that needs to be dissipated.
So I appreciate the opportunity to
comment on this. I hope I've made myself
clear. Um
this type of a annexation
should speak to our processes.
And when we have a process
where individuals come down to our
planning commission meeting for five
hours, discuss these very issues with
the members of the planning commission
and we don't have the minutes to refer
to. That's kind of up to my opinion and
I don't think that's probably the best
way to do it. This is a formal process.
It's very important and I hope that we
can take a look at it in the context of
not only this annexation
but the entire process here because
this is big
surrounding it is something much much
bigger
in the county that we have no say on.
So looking at the whole I look forward
to this discussion and I hope that
tonight we've [snorts] shown that we as
has been pointed out here um I hope
Microsoft is going to uh directly
look at some of these questions and
answer them. I there I got a lot to
learn. I don't I don't uh deny that. I
think people in the community do as
well. but you're coming into a interface
between the city and the county that
really needs our best efforts. So, um I
look forward to that continuing
discussion. Thank you.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Secret,
>> I just like to remind the governing body
that the planning commission does not
consider annexation.
It's not even a topic on their agenda.
Thank you,
>> Mr. Mayor, Mr. Amore, can we not remind
each other of things that we know
perfectly well?
I understand this process. I sit on the
public service committee.
I understand this process. They go
together
and the discussion from the public goes
into this process.
And I absolutely believe we've got to
stop this narrow interpretation and look
at the total impact,
look at the total amount of money, look
at the good things,
but we don't look at it in a in this
vacuum with this narrow focus. Yes. Yes,
sir. I am well aware of the fact that
the planning commission does not act or
make an a uh recommendation on
annexation. They make a recommendation
on matters directly related to that
zoning.
>> In in light of that that the planning
commission mayor does not uh take action
on annexation, I would call a point of
order that we need to move on.
>> Thank you.
Anyone else?
All right. The purpose of the public
hearing has been met and we'll move on
to the next item.
>> Number seven, ordinance third reading
amending section 13.20.050
general prohibitions and section
13.20.070
local limits of chapter 13.20 20
wastewater treatment and disposal of the
code of the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming to
revise local discharge limits and
related provisions in compliance with
NPDES and WPDEES permit requirements.
>> All right, we have before us rewrite of
our wastewater regulations and some
discharge limits and we'll go out to the
audience see if anybody in the audience
wants to speak to that issue.
>> Hearing none, we'll go to Dr. Aldrich,
please for a motion.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Emmens.
Comments from the governing body on the
ordinance.
>> Hearing none.
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes.
>> Since
if you'd allow me a little attitude, I
see Mr. Strong or Mr. Bulo, one of them
getting up. But since this does deal
with waste into the
um sanitary sewer, would would Mr.
Strong please address what our current
policy is in regard to the glycol laden
water from data centers?
>> Mr. Strong, are you part of that? Uh is
that part of this uh discharge limits?
>> Um through you, mayor. Uh I guess sorry
to you, mayor. No, the discharge limits
are I don't think it covers glycol,
>> but um we can't create a comprehensive
list. This is the local limits of of the
stuff that we regularly monitor going
into the plant. But to answer uh Dr.
Renie's question, because of the
potential impact of glycol to our
wastewater treatment plants, we're
actually requiring all the the closed
loop data centers that use them to build
a separate collection system that drains
to a tank and is not directly connected
to our our collection system so that it
can be evaluated. If they have a leak
and they say, "Well, there was no
glycol." We can test it before it comes
to our plant. or if it has a if it's
full of glycol, we can say no, you got
to haul it off and have it properly
treated in a facility that can handle
it.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. Anybody else in the governing
body? Madame Clerk, take the the vote,
please.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> I.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> I.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> Dr. Mr. Emmens. Yes. Mr. Esel.
>> I.
>> This ordinance is approved on third and
final reading.
>> Number eight, third ordinance, third
reading, amending and updating the solid
waste fee schedule in accordance with
section 8.44.010
of the municipal code of the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, and repealing
ordinance number 4621.
>> All right. This is our annual review of
our solid waste fees. And I think for
most people here, the numbers they're
going to want to hear is it's a 1%
increase in residential, 3% for
commercial. We'll go out to the
audience, see if anybody's here to speak
to our solid waste fee schedule.
Anybody?
All right. Hearing none. Uh, Mr. White.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve on third
and final reading. And I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Wolf. Comments on the
fee schedule by the members of the
governing body.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Okay. Uh, hearing none. Madame Clerk.
>> Mr. Esel.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> No.
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. White.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Hi.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> Mayor Collins.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Yes.
>> The ordinance is approved on third and
final reading with Mr. Moody voting no.
Number nine, Ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located
southwest of the intersection of HR
Ranch Road and Judy Lee Drive and
southeast of HR Ranch Road in Judy Lee
Drive from JL Ranch PUD planned unit
development to NR2 neighborhood
residential medium density.
>> All right, this is an older neighborhood
that uh um was under a PUD, but because
of all the work we've done on our
housing, actually now fits really well
into our current zone districts. And so
we have a zone change to get us to NR2.
Mr. Swain.
>> Uh, good evening, mayor, members of the
council. Brandon Swain, agent for the
applicant. Just wanted to make myself
available for any questions before the
final vote this evening.
>> Thank you.
>> I don't see any Brandon. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Anybody else in the audience?
>> Okay, we'll go to Dr. Aldridge for a
motion.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Emmens. Comments from
members of the governing body on the
zone change.
>> Hearing none. Madame clerk.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Escoel.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Labour.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Hi.
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. White.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Hi.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> Mayor Collins.
This ordinance is approved on third and
final reading.
>> Number 10, ordinance, third reading,
appropriating monies for the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, for the various
purposes in conducting the municipal
government of said city and fixing the
amount of general and special taxes as
part of the revenue required to meet the
said appropriation all for the fiscal
year beginning July 1st, 2026 and ending
June 30th, 2027. Well, hopefully tonight
is the last step in our fiscal 2027 uh
budget process. It's been going on for a
very large number of months. Um where
before us now is about an $83 million
general fund budget uh for the city of
Cheyenne. We'll go out to the audience
and see if anybody has any comments or
questions about our budget.
I see your hand up.
Mr. Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> Um, okay. Mayor Collins, members of the
city council for the permanent
administrative record, Charles Miller.
Um, just to verify, uh, this is
ordinance item number 10, the
appropriation of $232 million,9
232,954,329
for fiscal year 2027. Is that correct?
>> I believe that sounds right.
>> Um, okay. I'm issuing a formal
constructive notice regarding ordinance
item 10, the appropriation of that
$232,954,329
for fiscal year 2027. This ordinance is
a mathematical fiction. You are
preparing to authorize a ledger that
actively socializes corporate
liabilities while bleeding general fund
reserves for cosmetic optics. First,
let's audit the general fund. You were
appropriating 82,7507,
>> Mr. Mayor. And a has something to do
with the budget.
>> I'm sorry. This is about the the the
budget. Go ahead,
>> Mr. Mayor. Okay. Thank you. Um, you are
appropriating 82,765,26.
Yet section two of this ordinance
mathematic mathematically confesses that
to balance this fund, you're extracting
2 million uh71,857
directly from revenue from reserves.
Concurrently, this exact same ledger
appropriates 9,676,226
for community recreation and events.
This is the ma mathematical definition
of capital misallocation. You're
actively draining municipal reserves to
fund a $9.6 million discretionary
aesthetic budget while simultaneously
telling taxpayers you lack the funds to
repair failing residential roads.
Second, look at the board of public
utilities revenue matrix. The water
enterprise fund explicitly balances its
ledger on the back of $20 million in
unsecured loan proceeds, specifically
the state revolving fund debt required
to begin fixing the catastrophic toxic
lead service line crisis. You are
forcing the existing taxpayer to absorb
$20 million in state debt just to drink
clean water. Yet earlier tonight, you
authorized the unchecked industrial
sprawl of corporate hyperscalers.
You are utilizing the business park
loophole to exempt these multi-billion
dollar developers from the Wyoming
industrial uh sitting council sighting
council legally stripping our county of
the socioeconomic impact fees needed to
expand this exact infrastructure. You
are socializing the toxic debt and
privatizing the corporate profit. Third,
you are appropriating over 22.7 million
from the optional 1% sales tax fund. As
verified on the permanent transcript,
this is the exact fund this
administration systematically targets
for consent agenda laundering bearing
$384,000
engineering contracts. Mr. Miller, your
time's up. Thank you for calling.
>> Anybody else in the audience want to
speak to the uh budget?
All right, Mr. Crap, may we have a
motion, please?
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
committee of the whole is to approve on
third and final reading. And I so move.
>> Second.
>> It's been seconded by Mr. White. Mr.
Crave.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend to increase
the facilities maintenance division
equipment budget line item by 250,000
from general fund reserves to purchase a
fleet generator.
>> Second.
All right, we're going to go out to the
audience on this item. We have an
amendment to add $250,000 to our budget
to purchase a generator. The genesis of
this was during our big windstorm when
we lost power in Cheyenne, we couldn't
pump gasoline for fire trucks,
ambulances, and police cars. And uh so
we're going to add a generator to our
fleet maintenance facility so we can
keep our fuel pumps on and also to be
able to open the doors and be able to
get vehicles in should they need
maintenance. We'll go out to the
audience and see if anybody wants to
talk about that $250,000
addition to our budget.
Hearing none, how about from the
governing body?
>> All right. All those in favor of the
amendment, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed? That amendment is
approved. Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend to increase
the special projects division budget
parks and recreation projects line item
by 750,000
from general fund reserves for pavement
improvements at Lions Park and Cahill
Park.
>> Second.
>> All right. Before us, we have an
amendment. We have some of the parking
lots around
uh I guess the forestry office and the
botanic gardens that are in disrepair
and also in Cill Park. And so we want to
take a little money from our reserves
that we've been adding up over the last
few years and do some maintenance on
those uh uh those parking areas. Uh
we'll go out to the audience and see if
anybody wants to speak to this $750,000
addition.
Welcome, sir. It's nice to see you.
>> Thank you. Richard Johnson, 612
McGovern. Having ridden my bicycle here
uh this evening, um I'd appreciate it if
you could add Holiday Park to that list.
Thank you, Mr. Johnson. Anybody else?
>> Yes, ma'am.
Go ahead. Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> We always can hear you, sir.
>> Ah, okay. Um, Mayor Collins, members of
the city council for the permanent
administrative record, Charles Miller, I
am issuing a formal constructive notice
regarding the spontaneous mill
million-doll amendments currently being
bolted onto the fiscal year 2027 budget.
What this governing body is executing
right now is a due process vacuum. You
are presenting the taxpayers with a
static $232 million budget document only
to bypass public scrutiny by manually
extracting hundreds of thousands of
dollars from general fund reserves via
live floor amendments. Let the record
reflect the exact math occurring
tonight. In a matter of minutes, you
have
>> Mr. Miller, you realize we did this in
committee, right? So, this is not the
first time this governing body or the
public has heard about this.
>> Uh well, so these these uh amendments
>> Mr. Miller, are you aware of that?
Correct.
>> Okay. So, the
>> Mr. No. Are you aware of that?
>> Uh would you would would I be able to
finish my
>> I just asked you a question, sir. I just
was curious. Were you aware of the fact
that this came through the committee
process? So, it's already been through
one public hearing. This is a second
one. We didn't spring this on anybody. I
just want to make sure for
administrative record or whatever you
call it that we have uh we're not trying
to spring something at the last minute.
Sir,
>> uh Mr. Mayor, if possible, um maybe I if
you have questions for me, then I would
be able to answer them when my uh three
minutes is.
>> I'll add I'll add a couple time a couple
seconds to your time. I asked you a
simple question, sir. Were you aware of
it?
>> U so
>> that's okay. You don't have to answer. I
think we know the answer.
>> If you could if you could possibly ask
me that my qu the questions you have for
me after, then then I would be able to
complete my uh public comment and then
answer any questions you have after
that.
>> Go ahead, Mr.
Um, okay. So,
um, let's see here. Where was I? So, in
a matter of minutes, you have proposed
extracting $750,000
from reserves for park pavement and
another $250,000 for a fleet maintenance
generator. You have materialized $1
million out of thin air. The
administrative contradiction is
mathematically absolute. This is the
same governing body that has that
repeatedly claims severe fiscal poverty
regarding the $100 million unfunded
liability to replace an unknown number
of 28 thous unknown uh toxic lead
service line uh out of out of 28 thou
28,000 unknown lines. Uh it it is the
same administration that forces a new
algorithm based storm water
um I'm sorry give just give me a moment
here. Uh you you cannot mathematically
claim systemic poverty for public health
emergencies while utilizing the council
floor as an unitemized ATM for
million-doll discretionary amendments.
Bypassing structured public oversight to
alter the finalized municipal ledger by
voice vote is an absolute breach of
fiduciary duty. Your fiscal alibis are
neutralized on the permanent record.
Thank you.
>> All right. Anybody else?
All right. Hearing none. Uh we have a
motion to uh spend some money to fix the
parking lots. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> I. Those opposed?
>> No.
>> Mr. Moody is a no.
That amendment is approved. Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend to increase
the city attorney division budget by a
total of $158,626
to fund an additional attorney position
and decrease the city council division
general discretionary line item by the
same amount.
>> Second.
>> It's been seconded by Dr. Aldridge. the
city council set a goal to try to get
our uh abandoned buildings and some of
our nuisances here in the community
cleaned up. And one of the the facts of
that is is in order to do that takes
quite a bit of law time in our
attorney's office which we don't have
the bandwidth. So if we're going to meet
that goal, we need to add another
attorney's position. And that's what
this motion does. Anybody in the
audience want to speak to that?
>> All right. How about from the governing
body?
I already closed public comment. Mr.
Leborn, [clears throat]
>> Mr. Mayor, I I speak strongly in favor
of this uh amount and for this purpose,
it's uh something that really is
important and is uh bounces around from
various departments and really doesn't
have that tracking method that we're
going to need to handle these uh complex
matters. So, I think this is a real real
step in the well, it'll it's a solid
step. It's going to give us an
opportunity to do something we've wanted
to do for a long time. Thank you,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you,
um, I concur with my colleague from Ward
One. Again, as I said, committee the
whole I look at cities like Los Angeles
that have this problem and they're not
taking care of it. We don't want to be
like that. So, that's what I support.
Thank you. Anyone else from the
governing body on the attorney?
>> All right, hearing none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> All right. That third amendment is
approved and we're back on the main
motion, which is the budget, which is a
little bit bigger now. Anybody on the
governing body want to speak to that?
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, I would just
like to uh through you put a plea out
once again for Mr. Miller um to put
maybe on his permanent administrative
record to please come down and see us.
We would love to have him here um in
person. That would be great. And also I
want to remind everybody that the budget
is public record and it is out there and
it is available. So if you have any
questions after listening to all the
debate, please take a look at it so that
you can get a good clear understanding
of what all is in it. Thank you,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you.
I just want to again thank the treasur's
office, Miss Lockman, for all her hard
work. Um, I don't like every I don't
like everything in this budget. However,
I will support it because, as I made a
promise to those that are on the front
lines, they did get their raises, which
is the reason why I voted no last year,
but this year, I'm happy to see they are
getting those raises. So that's my uh
promise that I made up on his dis going
back a couple months. Thank you, Mr.
Mayor.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh Mayor Collins through you. Um I am
going to be in support of this uh budget
tonight as well. Um, I recognize it the
concern that uh we are taking money out
of reserve to do some things that are um
quite honestly long overdue like
repairing pavement in some of our local
parks starting on that project, being
able to get this emergency generator um
to that can be utilized for uh fuel and
fleet maintenance in uh when the power
goes out as well as adding a city an
assistant city attorney that will help
us to um proceed with hopefully
recapturing uh some of the um costs that
we invest every time we have to um
go and uh abate a property. Uh what I'd
like to remind people of is that when um
I came onto this council almost six
years ago now, um we had uh
not even 70 days in reserve and we now
have over 300 days in reserve. Um we
have been extremely fiscally
conservative. We've made sure and we've
reviewed things to make sure that fees
are covering the expenses um for the
expenses that are incurred for each of
those items. Uh we've been conservative
not knowing what our um colleagues at
the state legislature were going to do
with uh property tax um and not knowing
what the outcome of the initial the
constitutional ballot initiative will be
in November. Um but sometimes you put
money away in reserves in order to be
able to do some of these long-term
projects just as you would in your own
uh financial house. And so for that
reason, um, I'm going to be yes vote
tonight. But I want to I want it to be
noted that we have done this completely
in the public eye and that we have been
fiscally conservative so that we might
be able to begin taking on some of these
larger projects. Um, which I think our
council can be extremely proud of.
>> Any bills from the governing body?
>> I just want to take just a minute on a
personal level to thank our our u all of
our different divisions. I see a lot of
you guys sitting over in the corner
there. Our chief of staff, you guys
worked really hard on these budgets and
uh putting those numbers together and
then sending them off to our treasurer
and her uh department um Amber and
it's an amazing team, you guys. Um the
way that they were able to uh to work
through those budgets and uh every time
we'd ask a question um every time we
went to make a change, it was just
amazing how uh you know how well our
team works together. So, I just want to
say thank you to everybody that was
involved. This is a six-month process
for our our treasurer and uh a little
bit longer than that for each of our
departments. And so, I just want to say
thank you to everybody. I'm really proud
of everybody's work and I think we have
a great budget before us this time. We
took care of some of the things that uh
I thought were really important and we
really needed to take care of and I
think we're in a great place. And with
that, Madam Clerk, if you take the vote.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> heck yes.
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> yes. Mr. Esabel.
>> I
>> Mr. Lebornne.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> I
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Saggrave.
>> Mr. White.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> I.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> This budget is approved on third and
final reading as amended. Thank you.
Number 11, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located in
Cheyenne Business Park and Camp Stool
Business Park in eastern Cheyenne along
I80 from LI Light Industrial, HIV
Industrial, NCB Community Business to BP
Business Park.
>> All right, this is a zone change for an
existing business park uh to a new zone
district we call business park zoning.
and we'll open it up to the audience to
see if anybody wants to speak to the
zone change on third reading.
>> Go ahead, Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Hello, Mr. Miller.
>> Um, can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> All right. Um, give me just a moment
here.
Um, see
this is, uh, members, Mr. Mayor, members
of the council, Charles Miller, for the
record. Um, this is the,
uh, reclassification of land in the
Cheyenne Business Park and Camp School
Business Park along I80 corridor from
light industrial, heavy industrial, and
community business down to a unified
business park designation. Is that
correct?
>> It is, sir.
>> All right. Um,
I'm submitting I'm submitting this uh
comment to formally request a forensic
clarification on the operational and
fiscal drivers behind this
reclassification.
Shifting established zones, especially
heavy industrial, into a business park
reclassification carry specific
long-term infrastructure and tax revenue
implications.
Before this is finalized, the public
requires transparency on three strategic
points. Preemptive accommodations. What
specific future enterprise developer or
infrastructure project is this zone uh
is this resoning preemptively
accommodating? Zone changes at this
scale are rarely executed as mere
procedural housekeeping. Fiscal
architecture. Are there any pending
unstated agreements, memorandums, or
municipal tax incentives tied to this
new BP classification? We need to ensure
there are no obscured fiscal transfers
or concessions being structured beneath
this zoning change. And number three,
infrastructure load. How does this
structural shift alter the baseline
municipal service requirements
specifically regarding utilities, public
safety, and traffic load along the I80
corridor compared to the previous heavy
and light industrial designations. The
architectural shift this zone must be
justified by clear, publicly accessible
data regarding its true intent. I look
forward to your detailed response on the
record.
>> Thank you.
>> Anybody else?
>> All right. I hear none. Dr. Aldridge,
may we have a motion, please?
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading.
>> Seconded by Mr. White. Comments from the
uh Oh, we have a substitute.
>> We have an amendment.
>> Yeah, we do.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, I move to amend by
substitute dated June 1st, 2026.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Renie. This was just to
remove two land owners who did not want
to be part of the new zone area. And
we'll go out to the audience to see if
anybody wants to speak to the substitute
before us
hearing none. How about from the
governing body? All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. All right, we're back on
the main motion.
comments from members of the governing
body.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Yes.
>> Um, Mayor Collins for you. I just wanted
to address a couple of comments that
were just made by Mr. Miller. Um, I I
think it's important to continually
remind everyone that this um public
scrutiny does occur during our committee
process and that um our legislation is
not uh done behind closed doors. that
there is ample opportunities for people
to make comments whether at committee or
virtually virtually or here in person.
Um this he also referred to a new
business park zone that this was a new
zone. While it is the newest of our
zones um until we withholding the one
that's on the agenda for tonight um this
is not something that is being done just
for this particular entity or this
particular business park. and he also
asked about a structural shift. Um
when reading the supporting materials
and looking at the agenda uh which the
public has access to on Friday um before
each of our city council meetings
um it should be noted that this does not
result in any structural shift. Um
there's an assumption that was made that
this is being done to benefit one entity
or um a proposed entity and that simply
isn't the case. And I think that every
time the misinformation goes out um
during public comment or during a
committee meeting um is brought forward
that we need to make sure that we set
the record straight. Um that seems to be
a an ongoing concern um in our in light
of transparency. Thank you.
>> All right. Anybody else on the main
motion?
Hearing none. Madame clerk.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes. Mayor Collins.
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Emmens. Yes,
>> Mr. Esabel.
>> I
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Hi,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> No,
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Yes,
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. White.
>> Yes,
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> I
>> All right. The ordinance is approved on
third and final reading as amended with
Mr. Moody voting no.
Number 12, ordinance third reading,
approving and establishing revised water
and sewer rates, tap and system
development fees, administrative fees,
service charges, and penalties and
septic and commercial waste dump rates
as recommended by the board of public
utilities.
>> All right, this is an annual review, our
annual review of the board of public
utilities fee schedule. And if I
remember correctly, the the numbers that
are uh pertinent to I think most of us,
a 3% increase on our service fee, 5% on
water and sewer. Mr. Bone. Did I get
that right? I'm getting a thumbs up. So,
we'll go out to the audience to see if
anybody has a comment on the fee
schedule.
>> Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Mr. Miller, I've not been able to hear
you.
>> A couple times. Uh, I felt like I I
wanted to be heard and and definitely
>> Go right ahead, sir. It's your turn.
>> Um,
>> members of the council, Charles Miller,
for the record, I'm placing a formal
constructive notice of fiduciary
misallocation onto the permanent
administrative transcript regarding
ordinance number 12. This is this is the
ordinance we're on, correct?
>> Yes, sir. You are asking the taxpayers
of Cheyenne to absorb increased water,
sewer, and system development fees under
the guise of necessary municipal
maintenance. Yet, a forensic audit of
the municipal ledger reveals a severe
mathematical contradiction. Before this
governing body votes to extract higher
utility rates from vulnerable residents,
three documented fiscal realities must
be answered for on the public record.
The hidden reserves. You are raising
utility and waste fees on citizens while
the administration is quietly sitting on
over 77.3
million in unassigned reserves from
building permit windfalls. You cannot
claim poverty and squeeze the rateayer
while hoarding nearly an entire year's
worth of operating capital in offbudget
accounts. Number two,
the toxic liability deficit. We have a
documented $100 million plus unfunded
liability to replace toxic lead service
lines across the city. Furthermore,
internal BOPU records indicate a 30-foot
groundwater decline and a severe TCE
toxic plume at the Bellevore Ranch
Wellfield. Raising rates to balance a
budget while ignoring catastrophic
environmental liabilities is a failure
of fiduciary duty. Number three, the
hypo hypers scale subsidy. You are
forcing residential rateayers to
subsidize a utility system that is
buckling under the weight of
unmititigated industrial sprawl. While
you actively reszone thousands of acres
for water intensive data centers, you
are passing the system expansion cost
directly onto the citizens. A municipal
budget operates mathematically as a
zero- sum ledger. This rate hike is not
a fiscal responsibility.
It is an infrastructure bailout funded
by the taxpayer. Also, I had a a quick
question. It's it's gone on a couple
times in a few different meetings. Um
Dr. Renie had indicated the amount of uh
of water in the in the reserves and he
had indicated a number in the trillions.
I was wondering if he might be able to
uh actually uh correct that on the
record because our uh the acre
conversion the acre feet conversion that
he had given it was it was it was wrong
by trillions of he said trillions
instead of billions. I was wondering if
you guys could clarify that.
I think our firm yield every year is
about 7 billion gallons of water a year
on the record.
And Mr. Miller um
when uh when developers come to our
community including what do you call
them large hypers scale uh developers
the board of public utilities does not
put in the infrastructure the developer
does. So the rateayers in Cheyenne are
not subsidizing the uh the development
that happens when the school a school is
built the the school foundation puts it
together. When a small business person
develops they pay for the infrastructure
and when a data center comes they pay
for it. So sir while again I appreciate
your your calling in it is fundamentally
incorrect.
>> Anybody else? Dr. Emmens.
>> Um thank you Mr. Mayor. I would also
like to point out that BOPU does go
through an audit and that audit result
is probably
uh publicly available as well.
>> It is it's on their website for how many
years? I don't know a lot. Doc or Dr.
Aldridge?
>> Uh Mayor Collins for you. I would also
like to point out that um the irony that
uh item number one Mr. Miller listed was
77.3 million in permit windfalls in
reserves. And then the next item that he
noted was that we have a hund00 million
shortfall in toxic service lines which
um first and foremost we use reserves
for large projects and to anticipate um
those projects. Um we also know that we
are um applying for grants and things to
help with that toxic service line. It's
not that we're ignoring that or that we
have turned a blind eye to that. Um it's
simply that we are uh waiting for some
regulations at the federal level. We're
looking at some grant monies that are
available. We're they're we're doing our
due diligence. So um while we're being
damned for on one hand for having
reserves and damned on the other hand
for not spending enough money, I'm not
sure how we're going to make Mr. Miller
happy at this point.
>> All right, Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, Mr. Secret. One more item. I
[clears throat] don't know that we've
determined uh the amount of cost or the
extent of the lead pipe uh situation we
have in the city. Uh the last meeting I
attended with the BO poo um they were in
the process of examining records. Um
they've they've barely begun if they
have begun actually out in the field
looking at various sites. So, uh, while
we know we have an issue, I don't
believe we've, u truly established the
size of that issue or the cost of that
issue. Thank you,
>> Mr. Gabe. I think you're right. They're
out potholeing now looking to uh
identify uh where those those services
are and coming up with the mitigation
plan.
>> Thank you.
>> Did I get that right, Mr. Strong? Thank
you. All right.
Anybody else in the audience want to
speak to the Board of Public Utilities
um
fee schedule for fiscal year 2027?
>> All right. Hearing none, we'll go to Mr.
White for a motion, please.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve on third
and final reading. And I so move
>> second
>> seconded by Mr. Crave. comments from
members of the governing body on
this ordinance.
Dr. Aldridge,
>> Mayor Collins, you I'm going to uh be a
yes vote on this tonight just like I was
on the waist um increase. And that's
because um we have worked really hard to
make sure that um we are able to um
cover the expenses that we have, the
infrastructure cost, the cost of um what
it takes in order for us to do business
and to be responsible and to be fiscally
conservative uh rather than putting
these uh rate increases off and kicking
them down the road so that we end up
with a large increase later on. Um, so
this is part of our due diligence to
make sure that the um what we're
charging is covering our expenses and
that we're not um kicking it down the
road for another council to try and deal
with. So for that reason, I'm going to
be a yes vote tonight.
>> And to follow up on that, Dr. Aldrich.
The board of public utilities does a
longterm
uh cost of doing business study that
then gives them a guideline for uh a
number of years on what it will take for
them to be able to maintain their system
and keep up with inflation and
everything. And that's what this is
based on, not some guess, but that they
actually have a a consultant comes in,
looks at their system, which is almost a
billion dollars, to figure out what is
it going to take to uh make sure that we
keep our system in good working order.
And I think if we were to look at our
friends in Rollins and you would see
when their water system failed uh what
the consequences to community are. And
so while uh it's never fun to have to
change and increase fees, uh it's a hell
of a lot tougher when your system fails
and you're uh trying to boil water and
uh you can't bring new industry in
because you cannot um you can't handle
the the load. So, I commend uh both our
uh sanitation department and our um
Board of Public Utilities for their
constant monitoring of uh of what it
takes in order to make sure we have a
robust system. All right, let's go to
the to a vote. Madame Clerk,
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> I.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Esel,
>> I.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> yes. Mr. Moody,
>> no.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> The ordinance is approved on third and
final reading with Mr. Moody voting no.
>> Number 13, ordinance, second reading,
defining the terms and conditions of
employment for sworn officers of the
Cheyenne Police Department for July 2026
until the end of fiscal year 2027. These
are our annual terms and uh this one
includes a 3% market adjustment uh a
corporal rank a new corporal rank and
some updated and specialty pay. We'll go
out to the audience if there's anybody
wants to speak to the terms and
conditions for this year.
Hearing none Mr. White
>> Mr. Mayor the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve on
second reading and I so move second
>> seconded by Mr. Wolf. Comments from
members of the governing body on the
terms and conditions
hearing. None. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The ordinance is approved
on second reading.
>> Number 14, ordinance, second reading,
amending section 1.4.3 and 5.8.8 of the
unified development code and creating
section 5.8.9
carports to create definitions and
standards for carports.
>> All right. We have an ordinance um to
modify our unified development code to
allow carports on the front of a house.
And we'll go out to the audience to see
if anybody has any comments on allowing
carports.
>> All right. Hearing none, Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading.
>> Second.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend by substitute
dated May 28th, 2026.
>> Seconded by Mr. Moody. The first motion
was also um made or by Mr. Moody. Uh
this amendment removes uh in section C1
and C3 which was the uh zero setback. It
goes back to the uh the regular um u
the five foot uh setback that was before
the planning commission made that
change. We'll go out to the audience.
Does anybody want to talk about the
change in C1 and C3?
Hearing none. How about from the
governing body?
>> All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> Mr.
Dr. Renie.
Is a no. We're on the main motion.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend section Oh,
sorry.
>> Go ahead.
>> Move to amend section 5.8.9 8.9 C1 and
C3 to remove the ability for the
director to allow through administrative
adjustment for a zero foot setback from
a current or future sidewalk.
>> Is that what we just voted on?
>> Well,
no, she's saying no.
>> M Mr. Mayor, the the amendment dated
528, I believe. I think the attorney's
office could give a better explanation,
but it was a a administrative um
correction from the staff and then the
amendment that Dr. Aldridge just made
was the amendment made in committee.
>> Okay, I got that wrong then. Um Okay,
>> that's correct, Mr. Mayor.
>> Okay, so what was the one that we just
did that we probably need to go back and
discuss then because I I incorrectly
stated what it was
>> and I apologize, Mr. Mayor. I was
pulling that up as you were going
through it, but the the 528 one was just
adding uh the section basically adding
it to the headers of what all the
sections were. So it was kind of a just
a clerical correction um adding the new
uh carport section. Sorry.
>> So it was uh Okay. So
I think we need to go back and and and
do that one first and we'll come back
and do the second one. Um so I apologize
for that. We'll go out to the audience.
We had that 528 which was something just
in the entitlement itself that was
changed or was it in the
>> Mr. White help me out here. Mayor,
members, the council counterweight
planning and development department. So
the first subst basically the substitute
itself is to add I believe it is section
six of the ordinance uh which basically
just adds carports to
the basically it adds 5.8.9
to section 5.8 at the beginning of the
section in its table of contents. Um it
was just something that was missed in
the original ordinance. It's a clerical
error. Um it's just something we have to
have. So if this does get approved um
the UDC is updated correctly so that as
actually listed in the table of contents
for that section.
>> Okay. So this just adds carports in the
table of contents.
>> That is all the substitute is and then
the amendment was made in comm
>> which is one I thought we were just
doing. All right. I stand corrected. All
right. We'll go out to the audience on
this adding to the table of contents.
Anybody? How about in the governing
body? All right. Hearing none. All those
in favor?
>> I.
>> Any opposed? All right. All right. Now,
we'll go back to that other one. Dr.
Aldrey, would you say it again, please?
>> Mayor Collins, I move to amend section
5.8.9
C1 and C3 to remove the ability for the
director to allow through administrative
adjustments for a zero foot setback from
a current or future sidewalk.
>> Mr. Moody, you still good with second?
>> All right, we have a motion in second.
Again, we'll go back to the audience on
this uh uh removing the administrative
ability to have a zero setback, making
it five feet. Anybody? How about from
the governing body? All those in favor?
>> I
>> I.
>> Those opposed? Dr. Ready, are you still
a no?
>> Okay.
All right.
Now, we're back on the main motion.
Comments from members of the governing
body. Mr.
>> Mayor,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you.
I do urge my colleagues to vote. I as we
heard in the public services committee,
there has been a lot of people wanting
to put carports in. There are a lot in
not just WI three but throughout the
city. And again, five feet is pretty far
back from the sidewalk, 10 feet from the
curb. Just put a visual perspective on
it. And also to looking at from
affordable housing perspective, let's
say don't want to put in a garage, put
in a carport. That would definitely cut
down on cost if the developer or biller
decides to do that. So again, it's just
making it easier for our constituents,
but also potentially future developers.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> I have a question.
>> Dr. Alder, your question.
>> Uh, Mayor Collins, for you. One of the
questions that I have is that I don't
see as I read through this uh proposed
ordinance anything that requires these
to be
anchored in some way. And so I'm
wondering if we might be able to address
that.
>> Mr. White,
>> mayor, Conor White, Planning and
Development Department. So the anchoring
comes when the building permits
required. um building code requires
carports to be anchored down. So that
that is where the anchoring is. We don't
specifically have it in the zoning code.
If council wants to add that, you at
your discretion, you can add that in
there that these will be anchored. Um I
don't think it would hurt. Um it just
overlaps with building code, but if
council would prefer to have that in
there as well as another requirement,
but you can always add that with um an
amendment. So, this is only on second
reading. So, we do still have um
basically tonight and then committee in
another night. So, um if council does
want to make that amendment, more than
happy to draft up uh that amendment as
well.
>> Dr. Al, it sounds like it's handled, but
would you prefer to see it handled in
committee?
>> I have a follow-up question.
>> Yes, ma'am. Um when these if a homeowner
were to purchase a carport kit
um and do the work themselves, um
while we would highly recommend and it's
law that they get a public uh permit to
do that, correct? We know that a lot of
these go up over the weekend or u on
holidays when people are not, you know,
thinking that we're not watching. Um,
and so my real concern is that if there
they don't go through that process and
it's not in this,
I don't know quite honestly. I mean, I
guess we would have to enforce it
somehow when it flies off and, you know,
destroys the next door neighbor's
vehicle. Um,
>> yeah, they'll sue each other. Yeah,
that'll be good. And then, um, so I I
would like to, um, see something, I
think, in this ordinance as well. So,
I'll work on an amendment for uh
committee,
>> mayor, through you. I can definitely do
that. I can draft something up and have
that ready uh for committee next week.
>> Great. Thank you.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Uh Mr. Mayor, through you. Thank you. Um
I'm I'm totally perplexed by this
proposal. Uh something that is this
significant, and I shouldn't be speaking
to the people that are here. I should
speak to the people who aren't here. Um,
this is going to allow on people's front
of their house 600 square foot carports,
10 by 60.
So, you can basically fill up your
entire driveway with a carport now under
this ordinance. Uh, the current
ordinance requires these to be in the
backyards. Now, we don't enforce that
apparently or can't enforce it because
we don't have the enforcement u uh
capacity, but this is this is a huge
change and you'd think that more people
would be interested in it, but
apparently not. Um, so I've got I've got
a large concern about that. And these
things, I mean, they need to be
engineered with the winds that we have.
Um, it's They're a danger to all of
their neighbors, to their own house, uh
when they start blowing around in 80 mph
winds. Um
so I know we're on second reading,
mayor. Uh we've got another shot at
this, but I deep concerns about what
we're doing.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> All right, we're on second reading. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I. I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> No. May I see the hands and nose?
>> Dr. Rainey,
Mr. Wolf, Mr. Crave, Mr. White, Dr.
Aldridge, Mr. Leborn, and myself. The
ordinance fails on second reading.
Next item, please.
>> Number 15, ordinance, second reading,
amending section 1.3.11, nonconformities
1.4.4, definitions 1.4.5 4.5
interpretation of zoning map 2.2.7
special use approval 5.1.2 zoning
districts established and 5.1.4 use
table and creating 5.6.10
regional entertainment re overlay
district and 5.7.13 gaming center
development standards and setting an
effective date for compliance.
>> Well, we're pretty blessed that the
legislature finally changed some rules.
Uh, Senate File 45 gives
the creation or the location of historic
course racing casinos to the local
governance where they are. Currently,
they're approved by the gaming
commission and then sites are approved
by the county commissioners and we're
bypassed in that process. And so, now
that we have that authority, this
ordinance creates an overlay district
where they can be used by right. Um it
creates a uh a separation of where they
need to be um and a bunch of other
things that uh kind of limit and
regulate where um historic horse racing
casinos can go. We go out to the
audience, see if anybody here to speak
to that this evening. Anybody?
>> I want to start with the staff report. U
Mr. Bloom, mayor, members of council,
Charles Bloom, planning and development
director. I do have a PowerPoint
presentation put together that I could
go through if you all do desire, but I
just want to give a real quick high
level.
>> Is it a quick one?
>> Probably wouldn't be very quick. What I
do want to note is we have a substitute
that we are going to be presenting at
the public service committee to address
concerns that were brought up at the
last public service committee. Um, one
of those is to correct an oversight in
the ordinance when it was drafted where
as a special use that special use should
be allowed in the mixeduse business MUB
zone district. That has a direct effect
on one of the locations um that is in
existence today. Secondly, the other
item we've heard is a concern with the
modification that the planning
commission had made which changed the
separation requirements um from being
500 ft from a standalone child care
center to a child care center of any uh
type. Those are commercial operations.
So it would include ones that are in
retail strip centers. That was changed
to be mandatory. Um what we have changed
it to we're going to recommend changing
the substitute is that this not be a
zoning standard but it be a a standard
that you all can review in conjunction
with the special use permit um as a new
criteria 10 for your 10 findings you
would make where that would allow you to
look at them by a case-byase basis. For
example, maybe that child care is
actually uh shared with that specific
use itself because they want to have
that child care operation as part of
their their complex. Maybe that child
care is um across the street and around
a corner and is not even there. It'll
give you the ability and flexibility to
look at those on a case-byase basis. So,
um, also it allows one to look at any of
these, uh, sensitive uses, childc
carees, churches, recreation centers,
uh, parks, those types of items. It it
lets the governing body consider with
their review which one was there first,
uh, which one has been there longer. So
it would remove the opportunity for
someone to say I would hope this would
not happen to come in and establish one
next door to a proposed center just to
get an advantage. So this would become
discretionary. So that is what we're
doing. Uh we're going to move uh that
that forward at the committee meeting
and I'm open for any questions you may
may have on this. Well, M. Bloom, I was
going to challenge you to uh to do that
because, you know, I could see where um
someone could create a recreation
facility or uh a daycare and uh
interfere with another person's business
where the historic course racing casino
was already there and somebody moved in
to mess with their business, if you
will. So, I appreciate those changes.
They sound like they're they're right.
Did anybody on the governing body have a
question for staff?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> uh we'll start with Dr. Renie.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um would
director Bloom go over there? There four
overlay areas where
where historic course racing venues are
conditional use permit or use by right
and so could director Bloom please
review where those are.
>> Mr. Bloom,
>> mayor, members of the council, I can
definitely do that. Uh this is a GIS map
that we have put together. Um I'm going
to turn off a lot of the different
layers that are not relevant to the
overlay district. Um this is downtown
Cheyenne right here. I'm just hovering
the mouse around. It's the tighter grid,
the green, the purple. Um this is the
bridge for Interstate 180 that turns
into Central and Warren right here as
you cross over. Um the areas that have
been identified um as receiving areas
for historic horse racing facilities,
which are defined as gaming centers
under this code amendment, are areas
that we're looking at as primary
regional entertainment areas. So it
would be areas adjacent to the Reed Rail
Corridor, and this is from 23rd uh
street on the north all the way down to
15th Street. So it's properties that are
adjacent to the Reed Rail Corridor.
Um, also properties that are adjacent to
15th Street between the depot plaza and
the rail spur. Um, it would be
properties located uh south and east of
the alley. So, it's areas just fronting
the 15th street area. In these areas
here, this would not require governing
body uh approval of the land use. You
still would have to get your approval.
they would still have to get their
approval and your sign off through the
licensing provisions which that can be
accomplished outside of ordinance that
can be accomplished with a a resolution.
Um the second area is properties within
300 ft of Lincoln Way, West Lincoln Way
from Crow Creek heading to the west to
city limits. So this is 300 ft. Uh most
of these line up pretty darn close with
property lines, but it would be for
areas out here that are easily
accessible from Interstate 25 and
Interstate 80. A lot of this is to try
to um encourage redevelopment, encourage
investment in this area um and also
utilize some of the existing, you know,
accommodation infrastructure that we
have in the area through the new hotels
that have been constructed.
The final area is uh an area along
Interstate 25, which is uh designed to
really uh capture uh folks from out of
state. Not necessarily capture them, but
to attract them, I should say.
[laughter]
Don't want any more growth concerns, and
that's not the best way to grow. Um, but
what this is is it extends 3,000 mi or
3,000 feet uh north northerly and
southerntherly um parallel to the ride
ofway and it's any uh parcel that is
adjacent to Interstate 25 and within
2500 ft of I25.
Um what that results in is something
that looks like this.
The reason this is so large is because
this area down south, this is one large
parcel. So that use only is able to uh
be within 2500 ft um of that interstate
right of way measured perpendicularly.
This is the property line on this
property. This is a property line on
this property. So is this
those green and the purple dash lines
that you see right there, those are
major streets on our major street plan.
The purple dash line that is a collector
street. So that's a smaller volume
street. This green dash line that is a
minor arterial street that is High
Plains Road extension. So those are the
two receiving areas
um that we have. And while I'm on the
map I might as well just show you this
real quick for the zone districts.
Uh these areas here that are are colored
that are shown on the map. These are
areas that would be eligible for
consideration by the governing body as a
special use permit, which is an approval
process directly to the governing body
to make that decision. And then you
would be able to account um for any
potential
um uses that could interfere like childc
carees, churches, those places. Those
are not requirements to be set back from
them. They would be review criterion
that you could look at individually with
specific applications. Um, none of the
um ex existing facilities
would be um prohibited from having a new
license established
um with the substitute being approved at
public services on Monday.
I'm open for any questions you may have.
>> Dr. Reie, did you want to start?
>> No. Um, as far as question know, um, I
did want the public and my colleagues to
understand that
as I talked to many of you previously
just to understand that we are allowing
a conditional use permit in four overlay
districts and outside of those overlay
districts, permits are allowed, but they
will require a special use permit which
can only come from the governing body at
this point. So, um, I have a lot more
comments when we actually get to the
discussion, but thank you for letting me
ask that question, Mr. Anybody else have
a question for staff?
>> Yes, Mr. Wolf.
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you through you. Um,
this is this has been it's been
fascinating to see and I want to thank
uh Director Bloom and his staff and and
Dr. Renie for working on this. Um, I
think it's a testament to the quality of
the work that you've done that we've
heard nothing from the people in the
industry except part of the discussion
at the last week's committee meeting
that I attended. Um and um this is deep
zoning planning as all you have to do is
look at the maps and and and see this
and um so and it's indicative of how how
little controversy this has generated
because the headline in the newspaper
about all of this and the carryover
headline in the next page had a headline
under child care. um and so which is
only this affects these two properties.
So thanks for doing it. I know we're on
second reading. We'll have further
opportunity to talk about and I hope Dr.
Renie and and you director Bloom have a
chance to sort of give us a little
deeper background.
>> Mr. Cedric, Mr. Mayor through you. um
what protections are there for the uh
existing um uh providers that that were
approved by the county? I I just don't I
just want to make sure that we're not
going to go in and force someone to move
or close their operation.
>> Mr. Bloom,
>> mayor, members of the council, Council
Member Crave,
right now there is a state statute or
the state statutes are modified. Senate
File 45 was approved and it requires
that all existing licensed centers
receive city approval by December 31st
of 2027. It also requires that they file
that approval by July 1st of 2027. So
they do have a day when all of the ones
that presently exist in the city have to
come back to the governing body. Um Dr.
already has a lot more expertise on
that. He can talk more about how that
process works. The way this ordinance is
set up is there is a section in the
ordinance that basically mirrors Senate
File 45 and it says any previously
approved gaming center that we have in
the community that requires a special
use permit must come back to the
governing body for reapproval.
um that reapproval is is is anticipated
to run concurrent with that statutory
review authority that we have. The only
one um that exists today that would not
be subject to the uh special use permit
approval would be the one uh located on
High Plains Road and I25 and that is
because they are within that overlay
district. All the other ones they would
come back. we would review them against
our 10 criteria and make a decision if
they are appropriate at that location
and in addition they will look at that
statutory criteria which this does not
um conflict with that statutory
criteria.
>> Mr. Secret,
>> so Mr. Mayor, if I understand that so
there is no guarantee all of these
existing ones have to come back and we
we will have the opportunity to say yes
or no.
>> Mr. We could close them.
>> Dr.
If if I may address my colleagueu's
question um through you Mr. Mayor the
rationale for that the these licenses
are granted by the state gaming
commission on a one two or threeear
basis with three year being the maximum.
We wrote it into um we wrote it into the
ordinance that they would be reviewed
every three years by the governing body
um very similar to how we currently
review liquor licenses on an annual
basis. And Mr. Mr. Mayor, the rationale
for that was that and I want to state
currently we have an excellent
relationship with all of the HHR
providers in Cheyenne. They have worked
well with us. They're very responsible.
They work well with our police
department. We do not have an issue. But
um many of these started out local. They
were bought up by national corporations.
And I guess in the event that one of
their venues um the manager maybe isn't
too responsible, if if we have a bad
actor, we want to be able to review that
license at least within a certain time
period. And as I said, it's very similar
to what we currently do with liquor
licenses.
>> Mr. Cedar,
>> thank you, Mr. Mayor. Dr. Aldridge.
>> Yes, sir. Um
I just have a comment that as you're
working through the wording on this um I
think that commonly people inter
um interchange
daycare and child care and having been a
former childcare center director and
being an early childhood educator um we
do are caring for children not for days
and so if you could make sure that all
of our language always refers to child
care versus daycare um which is really
an inappropriate and degrading term in
child care circles. Thank you.
>> I don't see anything more, Mr. Bloom.
>> Thank you. So, we'll go out to the
audience. Jennifer, I see your hand up.
>> Uh Tracy Lake, you can go ahead.
>> Tracy, welcome.
>> Thank you so much. Uh Tracy Lakeok. I
serve as general counsel to Wyoming
Downs and 307 horse racing. I do want to
first thank the council for letting me
appear uh remotely today. Um I did speak
at the committee meeting and I I do just
also want to thank the planning
department
um their availability to talk through
this and work with us. I just really
appreciate it. Um we, you know, we do
request that the um current ordinance
before you be amended. Um specifically
related to the child care buffer, the
way it came out of the planning
commission, we have two of our
facilities right now, Persing and Ridge,
that would be out of compliance. Um a
couple of things to note. Um both
facilities of course went through the
conditional use process that's currently
in place um with the planning comm
excuse me with the board of adjustment
and um you know so we did go through
that entire process which of course
required a lot of um upgrades to the
outside of our facilities and our
parking and and our entrances. Um the
investment of these facilities has been
significant. We've invested more than
$20 million in the Persian location and
over $4 million in the Ridge Road
location. Uh to date, these locations
have generated a little more than $3
million in tax revenue to the city of
Cheyenne. Uh the Persian location, which
I know many of you have been to, um
operates a successful bowling alley,
arcade, laser tag, escape rooms uh for
all ages in the same building as the OTB
and we never had any issues. that OTB is
completely separated
uh from uh the all ages portions of our
building and and truly without that um
offtrack betting facility and that
gaming, the bowling alley, arcade, etc.
economically wouldn't be able to operate
independently.
Um all of our OTBs in the state are 21
and over facilities. And additionally um
as noted by um uh one of the council
members, we have a good working
relationship with the Cheyenne Police
and have no significant issues um to
date with our operation. Um we do um we
are proud to have uh some Wyoming
ownership um in our companies and we
take pride in being community good
community partners. Um the way that it's
currently drafted, it does create some
inongruencies. Uh for example, important
to note the rich location of course
operated as a bar and liquor store for
many years in that same location. And if
you look at the purging facility, the
office bar and grill, which offers a
smoking lounge um and bar even closer to
that daycare
um that's within Gold's Gym, um you
know, operates uh today.
Um we're working through with the
planning uh commission staff about the
exact wording. Um but you know with
these comments, we'd again just request
the council um to consider amending this
uh zoning change so that we don't have
two of our facilities out of compliance.
We've worked very hard uh to make sure
that those operate um in a good manner.
>> Tracy, I think we I heard from our staff
we're working on that and hopefully have
something for you to see at committee.
>> Yes. Thank you so much and I appreciate
the time. I'm happy to stand for any
questions. questions for the operator.
Thanks, Tracy.
Anybody else in the room?
Go ahead,
>> Jennifer.
Uh, Gunnar Malm, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Commissioner,
>> you have to unmute yourself.
commissioner. I know we can get that in
the city council. Sometimes it's harder
for county commissioners.
>> How about now?
>> Oh, there you go, brother. Welcome.
>> Um, so if you appreciate it, Mr. Mayor,
through you. If you grant me a little
liberty, don't want to speak exactly to
the zoning, but wanted to just uh
commend uh yourself and Dr. Renie on
helping us get to today where the city
has this ability. Um, I think the county
commissioners association and Wyoming
association of municipalities um, saw
this issue and it was brought to us all
by citizens and we worked hard on it for
a number of years to get to the point
where we were actually able to get a
statutory change that'll allow uh, this
kind of zone overlay. And I just wanted
to kind of touch on that and and thank
yourself and and Dr. Renie for your work
that you did at the legislature uh to
get the residents of Cheyenne um this
kind of voice in the game. So, just
appreciate it.
>> Commissioner, I think it was u a lot of
work by a lot of people with the uh
county commissioners and the
municipalities all working together. I
love that that we're doing that. Dr.
Renie did a lot of good job as Wham's
leadership um legislative leader. Um so,
again, really appreciate everybody
working together to uh I think do what's
right.
Thank you, sir.
>> Thank you. Appreciate you calling in.
Anybody else?
>> All right. Hearing none. Dr. Aldridge, I
think this is you.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading, and I so move.
>> Second,
>> seconded by Mr. Crave. All right. Dr.
Renie.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, as
Commissioner Mom alluded to this
and and as you mentioned earlier, at one
point,
um, approvals for horse historic horse
racing venues were given through the
state gaming commission and then
improved by the county commission. And
for almost all of us that sat up on this
um dis
um like a couple years ago when we seem
to get or maybe a little longer seem to
get have several of these open up with
around around the city. We all I think
back then that generated most of the
emails that we got was like why are you
allowing more of these and why don't you
do something about it and we had did not
have the ability to do anything about it
and so that's how I got involved. I was
part of a legislative working group in
2024 that advanced a bill that failed in
the legislature and went back and
reworked it in 2025 to where we did get
um as Commissioner M alluded to 27
between work for the Wyoming County
Commissioners Association and WHAM um
got Senate File 45 passed which now
gives us the ability to regulate these.
Um so
with that I approached Director Bloom
probably even before it got through the
legislature saying that look we need to
regulate this through um zoning as much
as we can and with discussion through
him and a lot of their work they did I
want to thank our planning department
they did a tremendous amount of work on
this every now and then he touch base
with me and and run it by me and I'd
give my suggestions but um as I said
they worked on this obviously for months
and this is the final product. This does
what many of us talked about months ago
when I first said I was going to go to
director Bloom and ask for an ordinance
and it does have the four overlay
districts where we think that where we
thought we would like to see or spur
some economic development th in those
areas. Um, it does require any place out
of those districts to come through us,
which is something that all of us at the
time said we wanted that ability. It
does, and I addressed the reason why
we're reviewing the licenses
periodically.
So, it does um it does all the things
with the exception of the one one thing
that came up in in the planning
commission. And as do director Bloom
said, we had a 500 foot radius
from any standalone one could not be
cited within 500 feet from any
standalone
child care center and it was changed in
um planning commission to all child care
centers which gives some heartburn to
two of our existing venues. Um, so I
want everybody to understand that that
will go to public service committee next
week. We will make that change back to
the original form which will be
presented to the governing body in two
weeks. So it's an or it's an ordinance
amendment on third reading, but I wanted
you all to be forewarned. So we're not
surprised by that at that point. So um,
anyway, Mr. Mayor, there's been a
tremendous amount of work put in on
this. both Wham, WCCCA, and especially
by our planning office. Um, it does
answer a lot of the concerns that were
expressed by all of you, my colleagues,
when when we were going through this a
couple years ago. So, I would hope that
you would support it. Thank you.
>> Anybody else in the governing body on
the ordinance?
I'm hearing none. We're on second
reading. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed? All right. This ordinance
is approved on second reading. We'll
amend it hopefully during the committee
and we'll see it back here in two weeks.
>> Number 16, ordinance, second reading,
amending chapter 15.20, National
Electrical Code adopted, appendix K,
International Building Code,
administrative provisions adopted of
title 15, buildings and construction of
the municipal code of the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, updating the
incorporated national electrical code
provisions as specified.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience.
Anybody in the audience want to speak to
the uh ordinance? As I understand the
law, when the state passes the new uh
new code revisions, we have 180 days for
the city to either adopt them or the
state takes primacy back from us. I get
that right, Mr. Chief Building Official.
Okay, that's where we're at today.
Anybody in the audience want to speak to
the electrical national electrical code
provisions?
I hear none. Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Been seconded by Mr. White. Comments
from members of the governing body on
the uh update to our electrical codes.
>> Dr. Renie, did you have comment? Nope.
Okay. I see none. All those in favor of
uh the ordinance on second reading,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed, this ordinance is
approved on second reading. Number 17,
ordinance, first reading, annexing to
the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming, land
located south of Charles Street, east of
Wanandi Avenue and west of McKinley
Avenue.
>> We're going to send this item to the
public services committee.
>> Number 18, ordinance, first reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of AR,
agricultural residential for land and
next to the city of Cheyenne, located
south of Tri Street, east of Wanandi
Avenue, and west of McKinley Avenue.
>> We'll send this one to the public
services committee. Number 19, ordinance
first reading, annexing to the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, land northwest of the
intersection of Clear Creek Parkway and
Ganet Peak Drive.
>> We'll send this one to the public
services committee.
>> Number 20, ordinance first reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of LI light
industrial for land annex to the city of
Cheyenne located northwest of the
intersection of Clear Creek Parkway and
Ganet Peak Drive.
>> This one will also go to the public
services committee. Number 21, ordinance
first reading, amending the official
zoning map of the city of Cheyenne,
changing the zoning classification for
land located north and south of West
Wallik Road and west of Interstate 25
from LI Light Industrial, CB Community
Business and PUB Planned Unit
development to BP Business Park.
>> We'll send this one to the public
services committee.
>> Number 22, ordinance, first reading,
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, land east of South Gley Highway
and south of Sweet Grass subdivision.
>> This one also goes to the public
services committee. Number 23, ordinance
first reading, amending the official
zoning map of the city of Cheyenne,
changing the zoning classification of AG
agricultural for land annex to the city
of Cheyenne, located east of South Gley
Highway and south of the Sweetg Grass
subdivision.
>> We'll send this one to the public
services committee. Number 24, ordinance
first reading, amending the official
zoning map of the city of Cheyenne,
changing the zoning classification for
land located east of South Gley Highway
and south of the Sweetg Grass
subdivision from AG agricultural MPU
planned unit development to BP business
park.
>> This one also goes to public services.
>> Better bring your J. Number 25,
ordinance first reading, amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located I 80 and
College Drive east of Southwest Drive
from MUB mixeduse business emphasis to
LI Light Industrial.
>> We'll send this one to the public
services committee.
>> Number 26, ordinance first reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
I80 east of College Drive from AG
Agricultural to BP Business Park.
>> Dr. That's nine straight items we're
sending to your committee.
>> 18, sir.
>> You uh you become the chairman and what
do we do? We load you up. So,
>> bring your jammies into dinner.
>> Yes, ma'am. Next item, please.
>> Number 27, resolution authorizing the
city of Cheyenne Board of Public
Utilities to discharge uncollectible
debts pursuant to Wyoming Statute
16-4-502.
>> All right. Before us are debts that are
four years old, uh that the Board of
Public Utilities can no longer collect
or have not been able to collect. And by
state law, we need to discharge. It's
$18,31724.
Does anybody want to speak to it from
the audience?
Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Hello. Can you hear me?
>> Yes, Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> All righty. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Uh,
council members, for the record, Charles
Miller. I'm speaking on item number 27,
the resolution allowing the board of
public utilities to discharge
uncollectible debts.
[clears throat] Excuse me. Um, just two
weeks ago, this council approved a 5%
rate hike on water and sewer and a 3%
increase in service fees, forcing
Cheyenne's workingclass residents to
bear the burden of Bo's rising
infrastructure costs. Tonight, you are
quiet quietly writing off uncollectible
debts because everyday citizens are
already failing to keep up with these
crushing utility costs. The math does
not work. You cannot squeeze residential
rateayers with constant rate hikes and
write off their bad debt while
simultaneously preparing to hand over
thousands of acres of our water
infrastructure to a trillion dollar data
center developer that refuses to provide
a finalized utility master plan. The
BOPU's financial model is breaking under
the weight of unmitigated industrial
sprawl. I urge this council to stop
subsidizing corporate land banking on
the backs of Cheyenne's taxpayers. Thank
you,
>> Mr. Miller. I don't know how we're
supposed to collect debts from people
who've passed away, but uh we'll take
that under advisement. Anybody else in
the audience?
Hearing none. I believe that goes to Mr.
White.
>> Yes, Mr. Mayor. The recommendation of
the finance committees to adopt an ISO
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Wolf. Comments from
members of the governing body. Dr.
Aldridge.
>> Sir, Mayor Collins, I asked for this to
be um pulled from the consent agenda.
Um, this is something that Board of
Public Utilities as well as our
treasur's office um have been working
really hard um during my term on council
and I'm sure long before that in order
to try and reduce the amount of write-
off that we have. As with any business
entity um that serves consumers, uh
there are going to be times when there
is debt that can't be collected either
because of death or bankruptcy as some
of these were noted um on the list that
we were provided. Uh sometimes it's a
banker uh the VA the Veterans
Administration um because somebody has
their house has been foreclosed on. Um,
but I think that we've made a really
significant dent and um, I was hoping
that uh, we might be able to um, hear
um, how much of a dent we've been making
in this um, effort to uh, get all of
these bad debts cleaned up. So, I know
there's been a lot of system changes at
Board of Public Utilities over the last
couple of years in order to be able to
try and reduce the um loss that we have
experienced through bad debt.
>> Mr. Bowen,
>> Mr. Mayor, through you to Councilwoman
Aldridge. I guess that I'll look at I
happened to pull the historical
statistics as I got into the room today.
Looking back in 2023, our write-offs was
79,185.
That did include about four years in
that current year. In 2024, our
write-offs were around 14,000 and our
write-offs in 2025 were 26,000. One
thing I'll kind of note in this is that
as a percentage of our revenue, this is
roughly 03% of the revenue.
>> Mayor Collins through you. I I think
that that is um it it really speaks to
the effort and the energy that's been
put in by um those that work with our
consumers and our citizens um in in
areas where they are they do accumulate
debt um for our services. And so really
appreciate the hard work um by the board
of public utilities and by our uh city
treasures office to really try and
maximize revenue and reduce bad debt.
>> Mr. Bowen, I haven't looked, but can you
tell me what the total revenues are for
the Board of Public Utilities on an
average year?
>> Mr. Mayor, that is roughly 33 million.
>> And we have $4,579.31
on average for bad debts. Well done,
sir. Anybody else?
>> Mr. Mayor?
>> Yes,
>> Mr. Mayor. I thank you through you. Um,
I just like to remark that this is all
part of regular business. Mr. Miller's
comments have no application here. Um,
even I I I would bet that GAAP
accounting requires us to do this at
some point to clear these off of our
books. Every business, the business I
was in as in a law firm has bad debts.
and you have to recognize it and you
have to take care of it. And I really
applaud what the the Board of Public
Utilities has done and and working with
the city and your office, Mr. Mayor, to
to get this regularly attended to. Thank
you.
>> Thank you. Anybody else?
All right. We have before us the uh
resolution to write off $18,31724.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The resolution is
adopted.
>> Number 28, resolution authorizing the
mayor to execute limited site access and
due diligence agreements for city-owned
property commonly known as Belbor Ranch.
>> All right, we have uh talked about as a
city council maybe doing some
development on the northeast part of the
ranch and uh we have some companies that
would like to go out and do some due
diligence to see about the uh uh quality
of soils and other things like that. And
so this resolution authorizes us to
allow people to go out on a temporary
basis to do some of those studies. We'll
go out to the audience. Does anybody
want to speak to this resolution before
us?
>> Jennifer.
>> Uh Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller, are you happy about this
one?
>> Can you hear me?
>> Are you happy about this one?
>> Uh well, I do have some things to say.
Uh Mr. Mayor, uh, council members, for
the record, Charles Miller, um, I'm
speaking on item number 28, and I
formally request that this, uh, well,
actually, sorry, um, the that this
resolution is not a routine
administrative item. It is a blank check
for backroom deals. By passing this, you
are granting the mayor unilateral
authority to execute site access
agreements for the Belvore Ranch with
unnamed corporate developers without
bringing those individual agreements
back to this council for a public vote.
I want to echo the grave concerns raised
by Councilman Wolf during the committee
meeting. The mayor admitted on the
record that the city has no intention to
charge these companies for access. You
are allowing trillion dollar
corporations to conduct free corporate
reconnaissance on taxpayer owned land.
Furthermore,
[clears throat] excuse me. Um,
sorry.
Furthermore, Councilman Wolf correctly
warned that there is absolutely no
certainty that the city will receive
complete environmental, cultural, or
wildlife data from these private
studies. This is especially dangerous
because internal Board of Public
Utilities records already indicate a
30foot groundwater decline in a severe
TCE toxic plume at the Bellevor Ranch
Wellfield. Outsourcing the due diligence
of a contaminated, highly sensitive
public asset to private developers
operating under non-disclosure
agreements is a dereliction of duty. I
urge this council to vote no on item
number 28. Demand that every single site
access agreement for Belvore Ranch comes
before this body for a public vote.
Mandates mandates strict data ownership
by the city and charges these developers
fair market value for excess. Thank you,
>> Mr. Miller. One thing, there are no
NDAs, sir, and you know that um we have
no NDAs with any of the companies that
are looking to come out on the Belleva
Ranch. They may have asked for them, but
we've chosen not to do that. So, you are
on the record, sir, told that. And I
hope I'll not hear that from you again.
Um anybody else in the audience?
How about uh and u Dr. Aldrich? May we
have a motion, please?
>> Absolutely. Mr. Mayor, the
recommendation of the public services
committee is to adopt and I so move.
Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. Mr. Wolf.
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor, I move to amend by
substitute dated June 8th, 2026.
>> Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Lelay.
Would you explain the substitute,
please?
>> Uh, I'd be glad to, Mr. Mayor, through
you. Um, I'm sorry I raised what are
characterized as grave concerns. I I
fully support the resolution. I fully
support the mayor having the powers to
do this. You and I had a very very
productive discussion afterwards. Um and
um the issues I raised were not in any
way intended to undermine this
resolution. In fact, they were just my
comments about uh maybe ways to
strengthen it. Uh the city attorney's
office has uh provided us with a
substitute um resolution that in fact
addresses the questions that that I
raised um involving uh both uh the
ability to to charge where appropriate
and and where the mayor's office uh
who's dealing with these companies um
can make the decision on that. Um it
deals this the revised substitute um
deals with the ownership of um the
information. Um it addresses uh the
questions about um excavation uh for
geotechnical studies. Um the um as I
wrote to the city attorney uh this
morning, these um these changes to it
are excellent. Um, I fully support them
and would ask the council to support
this uh, substitute resolution.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience.
Um, anybody in the audience want to
speak to it?
All right, hearing none, we'll go to the
city council. Uh, anybody on the
governing body?
>> Yes. Uh, Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, through you. Um could
um my colleague please explain the
differences between the original
resolution and the amendment or did I
just miss it? I mean the substitution.
>> Mr. Wolf, there's not a red line here.
So maybe you can just walk through the
things that you had added to this uh
resolution, please.
>> Um I'd be glad to thank you, Mr. Mayor,
through you and and thank you,
Councilwoman Emmens. Um they're the
basically the um additions here are on
the if you look on the first page on the
next to last and the last whereas
clauses
and um and then on the first whereas
clause on page two and um the one two
three four five six whereas clause on
page two. Um and then um those where
clauses are basically turned into the
language of the resolution and there on
um page three. Um they're incorporated
into the second paragraph, the third
paragraph,
um the fifth paragraph, and the sixth
paragraph. Um and um I'm totally
satisfied with the changes that have
been made and I I think uh this is a
this is a great thing for us to be doing
and I really commend uh council
president Seagrave for the work that
he's put in to the Belvoir along with
the mayor and his office and I think it
deserves our full support.
>> Dr. did that answer your question?
>> Um Mr. Mr. Mayor, you know, um, can you
give me a snapshot of what did you do
different? I mean, does it boil down to
a certain
different bent or
because I don't I didn't see this till
today and that might be my fault.
>> Dr. Emmens, Dr. Emmens, I think what it
is is that uh it includes uh
consideration for charging a fee to
access the the uh the ranch. uh what
what was said was um Mr. Crave uh and I
have uh authored letters that we've sent
out to companies asking them to come and
in those circumstances we didn't really
feel like we ought to be charging them
to uh to go out and look at the ranch if
we were the ones who invited them but we
wouldn't fully intend to charge somebody
who came to us uh to be able to go do
that. And then on the on the second side
of it, uh something that we talked about
internally, uh but we did not have in
the in the resolution giving us the
authority to do this was that we would
own the information. So whatever the
information that came out of the
environmental, we would own that. Uh
that wasn't in here. Although it was
probably not probably it was in the U
access agreements that we had proposed,
we just didn't have it in here. So this
memorializes to make sure that we do
that. So it was just things like that to
make sure that we're limiting what they
can do when they're on the ranch. We
don't want them out there digging big
holes and they're just out there going
to drill uh a few holes to see what the
soils are like to look for the
environmental things, Native American uh
type things, TP rings, wetlands, you
know, the kinds of things you would
typically do uh when you do an
environmental. So, it was really just
putting belts and suspenders on making
sure we didn't forget things when we put
the uh the access agreement out to uh
these different companies as they come
before us.
>> So, uh so Mr. Mayor through you. So did
or to you. So do do you feel like this
then
gives you the ability to do what needs
to be done quickly as or does it become
too over overburdensome?
>> Dr. Emmens, all of the things that were
included here are things we would
planned on putting into an access
agreement anyways. Okay.
>> A limited time frame. It's not an
open-ended thing. limiting what they can
do or making sure we had a list of what
they could do that we would own the
information afterwards. We learned that
from the Met uh MET uh information we
did with some of the wind providers
early. Uh they did the tow the the tests
decided not to uh do uh a development
and we lost a couple of years because we
didn't have the information. We learned
that one back in the early 2000s. So uh
all all the things that uh that uh Mr.
Wolf is is including are thoughtful and
really necessary things to have in an
access agreement. So, we're very much in
favor of it.
>> Thank you.
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor, if I if I might, just one
further comment. Um, Councilwoman
Emmens, um, I had the privilege in my
practice to deal with these kinds of of
agreements. Um, and so when I read the
first draft, there were just some things
that I I wanted to encourage the the
mayor and the committee to include and
and there there are around the issues of
of giving the the mayor to write the
charge if it's appropriate in
circumstances uh for this. um a very
common provision and then how you deal
with the information is is critical
because we obviously want uh to to have
the results of all of that. So those are
the two main ones. Uh the other issues
are are more minor. So thank you. Thank
you M
>> and Dr. Emmens or uh one of the things
that might be good is uh if somebody
wanted to argue with uh the fact that I
might have included one of those now I
can look back and say no it's required.
So it gives us a little little backbone
for that. Yeah.
>> Anybody else? All right. We have Mr.
White.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you. Um
I didn't get a chance to read this uh
until very late today. Um just between
getting off work and coming to the
meeting. Um, and I'm very usually I I
don't vote in support of amendments that
I don't really have time to to read
thoroughly and do some research on, but
I think from what I was able to get
through uh today and the explanations
that were just offered, I that I will go
ahead and support this and because
um because there are some things in here
that um provide some guard rails
and um you know our former colleague Mr.
Royel was uh was the champion of this
project and we're so close to the finish
line um which I think we're we're all
excited about. Uh so to have something
in place that provides some guard rails
for what can and cannot occur out there.
Um I think uh my former colleague would
be supportive of that and because of
that I'm going to support it as well.
Anybody else in the governing body on
this? Uh I guess we're on a substitute
at this time. Hearing none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> Those opposed.
>> All right. The substitute is adopted.
We're mech on the main motion. Anybody
else?
>> All right. Hearing none. All those in
favor of the uh the access agreement or
the resolution authorizing access
agreements, please signify by saying I.
>> I. I. Those opposed.
>> No.
>> This resolution is adopted as amended
with Mr. Moody voting no.
>> Number 29. Resolution authorizing the
acceptance of a donation for affordable
housing purposes and authorizing the
mayor to execute a donation agreement.
>> I'm [sighs] going to ask for just a
little bit of lenience here because I'd
like to tell just a quick story. Um, and
I've told it before, but um, four or
five years ago, I started looking at um,
how can we build more affordable housing
in our community? And, um, we started
looking out into our surrounding states
to learn, you know, how are they being
successful? And you look in Colorado and
Montana, um, Utah and all around us,
they were building, um, affordable
housing projects, and they were doing it
in a different way. They were building
it with uh low-inccome housing tax
credits using the 4% program. And uh
when you do that, it's uh
the federal tax credits help you uh with
the funding stack for that. The people
building the project uh help with the
funding stack, but there's almost always
um a local component to that, local
dollars that are required in order to be
able to build these these projects. And
typically, they're much larger than the
things we've ever seen here in Cheyenne.
And so, um, we've been trying to recruit
a company to come to Cheyenne and do
that. And we knew that, uh, we were
about three and a half million dollars
short. And I was at a dinner with the
CEO of Related Digital, Mr. Jeff Blow.
And, um, we were just having dinner
talking about the next day's ribbon
cutting, and he asked what the
challenges are that our city faces. And
I talked to him about water, and I
talked to him about uh, how our children
leave Cheyenne. and uh uh and don't come
back at unbelievably and alarming
numbers. And then we talked about
housing and related companies. Their
number one business is housing. They
really understood what we were talking
about. And so the next day at the ribbon
cutting um for the first time in my
adult life, I was speechless when uh Mr.
Blau said that uh uh the company
understood the challenge we were facing
that this is their core business and he
pledged to give us $3.5 million to
finish the funding stack so that we
could build an affordable housing
project. We have the Wasatch Group that
is a great group out of uh uh Utah who
um have have built these kinds of
projects all over the western United
States. Heck, they're building in uh in
the Ukraine right now for uh families
that have lost their homes there.
They're they're an amazing company who
uh who does this kind of work. And um so
before us today, we have the acceptance
of a donation for affordable housing.
Related R related Digital um is giving
us $3.5 million that will allow us as a
city to buy the 8.3 some acres of
property. And um the company will then
build a 184 unit affordable housing
project that will change the lives of
184 people who are living in uh housing
that they can't afford. And um we'll be
in a position to uh uh get some of that
back because they're going to lease that
that land back from us and we'll be able
to put this money back into a fund to do
another project sometime in the future.
So, it's uh one of the greatest
blessings I've seen in my 25 years of uh
since the time I was elected to the city
council. And uh that's what we're here
for today. Or this what item number 29
is, is uh this amazing gift from Related
Digital to uh the city of Cheyenne to uh
allow us to be able to um
finish the funding stack that we spent
the last four years trying to do. And um
so I'll go out to the audience if
anybody in the audience wants to speak
to this amazing donation. Um, love to
hear it.
>> Go ahead, Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> Oh, okay. Give me just a moment here.
>> You're happy about this one, right, Mr.
Miller?
>> Well, um, you're happy. Come on, Mr.
Miller. I don't think my uh um emotions
are really relevant here. Um but
um
let's see. Mr. Mayor,
uh council members, for the record,
Charles Miller, I'm speaking on item 29.
This resolution authorizes the mayor to
accept a charitable donation for
affordable housing.
The mayor recently bragged about a 184
unit affordable housing project, stating
on the record that the city is applying
for state grants and begging for federal
money just to afford to buy land to fix
our housing crisis.
It is the height of a municipal
hypocrisy to pass a hat around for
affordable housing donations while this
exact same council is preparing to
eradicate hundreds of acres of
masterplanned residential land for
corporate data centers. Your own
planning department stated verbatim in
the read land staff report that
sacrificing our residential zoning for a
business
>> point of order that these comments do
not
>> general welfare of the community
>> do not relate to this at all
>> Mr. Miller I'm sorry the council doesn't
think your comments are relevant and I
agree
>> um thank you anyways
>> thank you anyway sir
Mr. I'm Miss Madrid. Welcome, ma'am.
>> Heather Madrid, Harmony Meadows. Um, I
think this is wonderful donation. Um, I
think it would be great if we could get
some community benefit agreements in
place before they are allowed to build
here that the community has a say in
what we need. Um, and maybe I don't
know. I kind of have no idea what I'm
talking about here, but like a community
impact fund where a certain percentage
of project,
you know, investment is donated to a
community impact fund where the
communities that are going to be most
affected by these data centers get to
decide where where it's used. Um, but
additionally, I worry about the
affordable housing thing because
low-income housing is typically a
poverty trap. Um, if people ever want to
better their lives or make more money,
they will be evicted. People People
don't really want to live in low-income
housing for the rest of their lives. I
think they would much rather have a
home. Um, and again, while this $3.5
million is a generous donation, I think
in today's
housing market, that might be like eight
houses. Um, so that's all. Thank you,
>> Miss Madrid. I would just share with you
that a large number of our residents
that are in that 60% AMI category are
living what we call burdened homes where
they're paying like half or more of
their total income towards rent. These
will be targeted to put them at 30%. So
the whole idea is is that gives them a
chance to get stabilized to start saving
some money and then to work their way
out to uh maybe hopefully buy a home uh
sometime in the future. That was our
goal. But when you're you can't get out
of a hole. I
when I first got elected mayor, Tim
Wilson, he used to join the board of
public schools told me the first rule of
holes is when you're in a hole, you got
to quit digging. And uh when you're uh
in a situation where you can't afford
where you live, um you that that's a
challenge and that's where we're at with
a lot here in Cheyenne. So the challenge
is if we can get them into a homes that
they can afford, that stabilizes their
finances, gives them an opportunity to
put some money away so they can move
into
a home of their own sometime down in the
future. And so that's our goal is not to
make this a permanent place for them to
live, but a place where they can live
while they work towards getting
themselves out because the numbers of
people who are what we call burdened
over 30% in Cheyenne is it's it's a very
high percentage, especially people in
this category.
>> Go ahead.
>> Okay, thank you. Um, so is this
low-income housing or am I
misunderstanding?
>> This is this is affordable housing. It
is restricted to people based on their
um on their their wages and it's
basically targeted at 60% of the
adjusted median income for the county.
>> Okay.
>> So, a family of four making 90ome,000
would actually qualify to live here. Um,
>> yeah. Again, I mean, I don't like to
talk about what my background is, but I
am 100% supportive of people who are
struggling. I I that's literally what I
dedicate my whole life to is helping
people who are struggling.
>> Good for you.
>> Um I just worry about the rest of us who
don't fall under that, you know, federal
poverty guideline or whatever the
criteria is to get into these homes
because we're all struggling. Housing is
generally unaffordable. I'm pretty sure
more than 30% of my income goes towards
housing. Um but I don't qualify for any
help. So I would just say that if it I
yes to this project 100% affordable
housing. love it, but let's also have
homes that are affordable for general
people that kind of fall in the gap of
being in poverty and also can't really
afford a home either. I I would just
appreciate that. You know, Heather, we
did some research and uh and looked at
different studies and there's a thing
called the vacancy effect. And what we
found is that when we build houses like
this, these people are going to move out
of the houses that they're in that are
market rate. And it actually helps
stabilize the cost of housing or maybe
in some places even lower the cost of
housing for people who are not getting
this because it's a supply and demand
thing. And if we can create more
affordable housing to get people out of
the market rate housing, then it opens
up more market rate housing. And so, um,
I know it sounds, uh, it sounds weird,
but, um, uh, studies from around the
world have actually shown that, uh, by
by doing this, by adding housing,
whether it's either at the market level
or at the affordable level, actually
does help stabilize housing prices and
maybe even makes them lower.
>> Yeah.
>> So,
>> I just I just hate to bring everything
back to data centers, but where are we
going to build houses if we don't have
any land left? We're using our land for,
again, I am not opposed to affordable
housing, but where are there going to be
homes built? because our land is
disappearing rapidly and I'm worried
about that. That's all.
>> Understood. Thank you for being here.
Anybody else?
>> All right. I don't hear anybody. We'll
go to Mr. White.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to adopt and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Secret. Comments from
members of the governing body.
>> I just had one question.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins. Uh my question is you
talked about the uh lease that would the
land would be leased from
the owners of this the structure into an
account that the city would be able to
reinvest. And is that in perpetuity or
is that only for a set amount of time? I
don't see it on this document.
>> I think there's another lease agreement
and I think it's 50 years if I remember
correctly. Um Jaden's nodding his head
at me, but it's a 50-year lease. Thank
you. I just didn't see it in this.
>> Yeah, there's a second document, ma'am,
that's that's coming. Yeah. Anybody
else?
All right. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> Mr. Moody is a no.
This donation agreement is gratefully
accepted. Appreciate it.
>> Next item is number 41A on page seven.
Real estate purchase agreement between
the city of Cheyenne and KT Land
Holdings LLC for 8.37 acres of land
located at lot 1 block 1 scenic
development 8 filing a portion of
section 20 township 14 north range 66
west of the 6th PM Laramie County
Wyoming.
>> All right, we just talked about the
donation that we got. This is a piece of
property that we're going to buy. It's
8.37 acres. Uh it's on the corner of uh
Converse and
Carlson. God, I can never remember
Carlson. Thank you, Mr. Crave. Um and it
will be uh like I said, 184 unit. We'll
buy this piece of property and then um I
think in our next meeting, we'll have a
lease agreement that will come before us
to uh have the company lease it back. Um
so if you guys know where the fire was,
that unfortunate fire, it's literally a
corner to that location. If that gives
you a sense of where this would be at.
Um, so anyways, um, we'll go out to the
audience if anybody wants to speak to
this land purchase.
Okay, Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> All right,
>> Mr. Miller, just before you start and
I'll Would you stop this time, please?
Mr. Miller, realize the only way we can
spend this money is for affordable
housing, right? We don't have a choice.
Okay. U Mr. Miller, do you realize that?
U if if possible, I'd like to get my um
my go if you have questions and then I
I' love to chat after the initial
comment. Um thank you. Uh
>> Mr. Mayor, council members, for the
record, Charles Miller, I'm speaking on
item number 41A, the real estate
purchase agreement for 8.37 acres of
land.
Um, you cut my microphone earlier. Um,
but you cannot hide the facts of this
housing crisis. The mayor just admitted
on this microphone that he had to rely
on a $3.5 million corporate bailout from
a tech CEO just to fund this exact
housing project.
He has also publicly admitted that he
begged Senator Cynthia Lumis for federal
money to buy land for housing. But the
ultimate insult to the workingclass
people of Cheyenne is this. While the
city begs for charity to buy these eight
acres, Senator Lumis' own family is
poised to make an estimated $64 million
selling 3,000 acres of land directly to
Microsoft for the Highlands
>> point of order. I fail to see how this
could transaction,
Mr. Bill, I see no nexus here.
>> I guess my point is is that you cannot
beg CEOs for charity to build 184 units
while letting the political elite cash
out on 3,000 acres that destroys our
residential.
>> Mr. Miller, you're off you're off base,
sir. I apologize. You got to go.
All right. Anybody else in the audience?
All right. Hearing none, Mr. White.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve and an
amount not to exceed $2,645,000.
And I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Aldridge.
>> Comments from members of the governing
body.
>> Mr. M. Yes, ma'am.
>> Um, Mr. Mayor, through you. Um, I want
to because I wasn't my brain wasn't
working fast enough on the last item
because it's after 9:00.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> I just want to say that um I really
appreciate Miss Madrid's comments
because I think we need to keep in mind
that this is another piece of the whole
puzzle. this isn't the solution for
everything, but hopefully it'll be one
piece that will help people be able to
be safe and also um be able to move
forward with their lives. So, I think
that's really important for us to to
keep in mind that there's no silver
bullet on this, that this is another
important piece. So, thank you for that.
>> It literally comes down to more is
better. And Miss Madrid, I was thinking
about it afterwards. you know, we
changed a lot of our uh our regulations
in our UDC. Um we're seeing homes being
built now um on smaller lots, a little
bit smaller homes. Reminds me of the
1950s. If you drive through the avenues,
you know, 3,000 foot lots, 950,000T
homes. Um we're we're building a lot of
those now. And uh I think you're going
to start seeing a big difference in uh
the amount of homes that become
available.
Um
I mean, the developers are really seeing
it. I mean, the this governing body
worked really hard to to make that
change, and I think we're going to start
to see more more of those homes. And the
great part about that is we can build
three homes where we built one before.
And uh and I think that's what it's
going to take because the cost of
housing has gotten so expensive. Yeah.
All right. Anybody else in the governing
body?
Uh for the record,
um Mr. Miller talked about me begging
Cynthia Lumis. Um I did talk to Senator
Lumis' office. Um, if you look at
Montana, if you look at Colorado, you
look at Utah,
difficult development areas, qu uh
qualified census tracks are everywhere.
I mean, their map is colorful. And then
you look at a map of Wyoming and it's
nothing's on there. I mean, there's a
couple little pinprints and basically
what those are is those are tools that
um the IRS and HUD and other people have
done to make building housing,
especially affordable housing, easier.
It basically gives you 30% more tax
credits in order to build your projects.
For some reason, Wyoming has been
ignored. And what we've done is taken uh
Senator Lumis' office um a little bit to
task. Not it's her fault, but that she's
there to to try to lobby for us to have
the uh the Census Bureau look at our
areas to see if we can get more quality
qualified census tracks. They're
deciding there's not enough information.
that's their job to go out and do the
studies to make sure the information is
here and the difficult to develop areas
um are an incredibly powerful tool. And
so we've asked to be treated like
Montana, to be treated like Utah, to be
treated like Colorado so we can have
those designations and give our
residents and our developers the same
ability to build housing as our
neighbors have. And so that's and if
that's begging, I guess I was begging.
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> Mayor Collins, uh through you. Um I have
to say that I would be extremely
disappointed in you if you were not
advocating on behalf of our community
and our citizens. And um it's difficult
to understand how that could be seen as
begging when all we're asking is for a
reinvestment in our state and our
community with tax dollars that our
citizens have paid into the national
coffers and um would like to see some
benefit um come back to our state. So,
um, if that constitutes begging, by all
means, um, we need to keep begging.
>> Thank you, Dr. Alders. All right.
Anybody else on this real estate
agreement?
>> All right. I hear none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying, "I."
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> This real estate agreement is approved
with Mr. Moody voting no.
>> Next item is 42D on page nine.
Contract modification number two to
contract number 8199 between the city of
Cheyenne and HR Engineering, Inc. for
the 18th Street Reconstruction Project.
Had to get on the right page. All right,
we have before us a um a uh contract
modification. We learned that uh what we
were doing on our 18th Street uh project
would have overwhelmed the creek and we
needed to uh add some additional
hydrarology work to uh make sure that we
didn't hurt the downstream folks from uh
the good work we're trying to do to keep
the u uh downtown from flooding. And so
we'll go out to the audience to see if
anybody wants to speak to this contract
modification on 18th Street.
I hear none. Mr. White,
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve in an
amount not to exceed $313,197.
>> Second.
>> That was seconded by Mr. Moody. Comments
from members of the governing body.
>> Mr.
>> Mr. Mayor. [clears throat]
>> Yes, sir. Mr. labor.
>> This is a
very interesting change order that
brings forward a number of uh nearby
issues or even on the same site. Mr.
there. Um, if there's a question about a
major
drainage project coming through that
area,
I think we need to really think about
what else is planned there and what else
might be there and what else people talk
about because
as I guess we must remember,
the wetland down at the pump house area
is not a detention facility.
it is a pass through. So, what you're
really talking about here is a much
bigger flow
that uh is outside this contract, I
might add, that might someday
go on property adjacent to that area
that's owned by the UP Railroad. And you
also have the consideration of going
under the track.
So, I think that uh I'd be very
interested in maybe uh the city engineer
can help me with this. I'd be very
interested in some uh [snorts] as a part
of this contract that we do some uh
actual uh mapping and look at what's
conceived there and what might go there
so that we can make better decisions.
it. Uh this is a really significant
change going into a very congested
uh area that's
in some cases owned by the city, in some
cases not. And uh so I'm wondering, Mr.
Mayor, if uh the city engineer would
commit to uh
working with us to take a look at what
it might be uh appropriate there and the
mapping that would allow everyone to
understand this better.
>> Did you understand the request, Mr. Cob?
[cough and clears throat] Mayor through
through you, sir. To Councilman Liber, I
don't understand what you mean by
mapping, but um if you could clarify
that, please.
I think mapping is a pretty
wellestablished [laughter]
>> maybe just where the mapping
>> Mr. Mayor
uh and my my big concern as you well
know uh Mr. God is the fact that we have
planned and uh hope to someday have an
underpass
uh from the Greenway coming down from
the uh [snorts]
perhaps someday uh Reed Avenue corridor
and how that uh concept which I believe
we do have a schematic design from our
consultants on would interact act with
this uh major drainage project
and really take a look at where uh that
area is owned by the city and where it's
not and what the status is of that
conversation with the UP Railroad. I
think people need to understand
that I don't know why the pump house is
cursed as it is, but uh this is a a
major drainage project coming in that
same immediate vicinity that definitely
would affect um whatever we choose to
do. So it would be delineating the
spaces,
identifying them as to ownership,
looking at uh what we have paid for in
terms of that design and really looking
at it. And the reason I mention this uh
Mr. mayor and members of the council.
It's just a really uh congested area
with the uh state highway railroad
um property owners and as well as a long
planned uh project immediately uh
downgradient. So um I think that
probably for this uh
$313,000
we could get some maps. I think I
understood what he's saying. Did you
catch it,
>> Mayor? I think Yes, sir. through you,
sir. To council labor. So, sir, I've
already done that. So, I have a series
of three projects that I I've laid this
already out. Um there's three separate
projects that are looking at this. So,
downstream of this, I've got GLM working
on the Clear Creek Inline Detention
Facility and Dry Creek Siphon. I mean,
sorry, uh, Crow Creek Siphon to take
water to the south that works in
conjunction with this project. Also, I'm
looking at the purchase of the property
south of this area in the UP area. So,
it's already laid out schematically just
like you'd like. I'd be happy to go
through it in my office. Anytime you
want to make an appointment, we can go
through it in more detail.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. Anybody else in the governing
body want to speak to the contract
modification?
>> Mr. Mayor?
>> Yes, Mr. White. uh through you just
pointing out on page six of amendment
two of this contract modification it
does say surveying base mapping.
>> Thank you Mr. Dwight.
Anyone else hearing none. All those in
favor of the contract modification
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed this contract modification
is approved.
>> Next item is number 44A voucher report.
>> All right. Anybody in the audience or
online that would like to speak to the
vouchers?
Hearing none. Next item.
>> Other business.
>> Anybody in the
Mr. Johnson? Did you want to speak to
us, sir?
>> Thanks for sitting through our meeting.
We miss you.
>> I can't say the feelings reciprocal
after listening to all this garbage. Um,
so I bring several things uh forward. um
some of just observations of what took
place tonight, but I came down here for
other reasons. So, in regard to uh uh
one of u my neighbors uh recently I made
a phone call to the um after hours
police department for animal control and
then was called back by the um officer
that uh basically wildlife cannot be
picked up by animal control. And so, uh,
they gave me a number for a wildlife
individual that will come out and trap
them. What comes with that is an actual
cost to this because because animal
control will only pick up um, domestic
animals. So when we were all out there
in the neighborhood instead because it's
not good to discharge a firearm because
the bullet might go through the raccoon
and into your neighbor's home, you know,
we all joked around that um technically
a a crossbow bolt would actually be
quiet and just take care of it and you
if you weren't caught, you wouldn't have
a fee. But, you know, and then I ran
into the director of compliance on
Friday and I said, you know, it's would
be a very interesting uh question to see
if a an individual was to actually get
caught for this if they were to go to
court and fight this, whether or not
their ticket fee would be less than the
actual, you know, cost of pay, you know,
your ticket versus the cost of paying
for the removal. And so, you know, we
talked about that that that was
something that animal control really
doesn't do anymore as far as the traps,
you know, even in regard to that. And I
can let Eric, you know, kind of speak on
that in regards to what our
conversation.
Um, once again, uh, you know, I didn't
see a lot. I I talked with Jason at the
last coffee and council about this and
like I said I rode through Holiday Park
again tonight and so um Jason let me
know that with the geese because I had I
couldn't didn't know the name of the new
dog since Flo had retired that I guess
the dog's name is Jill but Jill actually
goes out you know to the parks to clear
out the geese but the geese are actually
being nested and catered to by residents
that live outside of Holiday Park and
then So therefore, he can't really like
do any kind of effective measuring. And
then there's guidelines under the game
and fish that don't allow him to do much
more than that. And so I mean, in just
one walk around the park on a lunch
break, I saw two different individuals
come from inside the or outside the, you
know, in the neighborhood into the park
that were bringing bread to actually
feed the geese. Even though there's
there's, you know, signs everywhere, but
just on my 30 minute walk, I saw two
individuals doing this. And so here I
am. you know, I don't feed them. I don't
like it. Wildlife period. And so they um
so all of a sudden, you know, I'm
getting hissed at and chased by these
birds, you know, because people are
still feeding them even though signage,
you know, and it's and it's
unfortunately Jason's kind of like
Richard, my hands are tied and the dog's
doing it the best it can. But I said, I
haven't really seen any PSA on an
individual. You guys really time me on a
other business that's not even a topic.
Um [laughter]
wow. Okay. So, um then the next thing to
talk to your, uh greenway coordinator,
um on the underneath the College Drive,
uh greenway corridor, they've ripped
another hole in there so you can get
onto the tracks. So, you might want to
talk to the greenway coordinator in
regards to that. Um I've almost been hit
twice. Um, once it's funny cuz the RV
law, you know, went back into effect,
you know, on Memorial Day and a car
jetted out of its driveway and couldn't
see me on my bicycle, you know, with the
because the RV was now parked on the
road. I hit my brakes. They didn't. And
then even downtown today, you know, I
was the one that did my brakes and
because they didn't pay any attention,
you know, there was no RV downtown, but
they didn't pay attention. So, I don't
know if that's something that you guys
can do as far as another bicycle safety,
you know, PSA to, you know, make sure
that people actually do watch out not
only for motorcycles, but also for, you
know, uh, pedal bikes. Um, I did want to
say thank you to Councilman Moody for
unblocking a lot of people off of his
campaign page. You know, that kind of
fell into the Supreme Court ruling that
I'm actually now allowed to see, you
know, political dialogue where
previously I was uh, blocked. Um just
observations on tonight. Um you guys
called more point of orders than I've
ever heard in regards to the public
under public comment. I get it that uh
Mr. Miller's a little bit irritating and
repetitive in regards to some of his
conversations, but um he is kind of
gaining traction amongst the community.
People have asked me, you know,
especially because of the campaign
season if I miss being on council and
I'm like no. And then one of the first
things they always ask me is like, hey,
do you know this Charles Miller guy
because he's really gaining some
traction. So people are starting to pay
attention. So I get it. It's irritating.
I've sat up there, you know, as well,
you know, with their the dialogue just
like me gets a little winded, but he is
gaining traction and people in this
community are taking him a little more
serious in regards to his dialogue. And
so, you know, it you know, optically in
uh by people's in the community, they're
looking at it that you're uh shutting
him out and shutting him down and you
know, what looks like could be First
Amendment type stuff. um in regards to
conversations that took place, you know,
early on. Um I got nervous when I saw
this stuff online in regards to um I
mean the the gift was, you know, done
publicly, but a you know, conversation
was done in regards to uh like UNC or
incoming data centers, in regards to
paying for a rec center. And I mean, I'm
no attorney, but it definitely started
to go into more of a quidd proquo type
of thing where all of a sudden the
governing body looked like in order to
come and do business here, like, you
know, we'll let you come in and do your
data center, but you're going to do
this. I mean, the Menard's thing was a
little different because it was
city-owned property that, you know, we
that we were able to do, but if you
know, they're bringing in annexation,
you know, then I I don't really like the
stipulations of like you're going to be
giving us a you know, a gift of a rec
center. I just think that kind of
legally in my world, and granted, that's
just my opinion, that it just seems a
little bit odd. Once again, optically
it's a little weird me sitting here
looking at the Microsoft reps uh sitting
with the planning department just like
kind of looked like there was a little
more um in cahoots.
Um
>> Mr. Johnson, we've given you a lot of
leeway. You're way over your time, sir.
>> I know. So, there's other positive
things though. So, if you'll allow me
some grace.
>> Can you do it quickly?
>> Well, I'm talking slow because usually I
got told I talk too fast. Um so,
>> Mr. Johnson, I'm serious. We I
understand we have a lot of the people
want to talk and we got an executive
session yet tonight. So
>> yes, I I understand that. So,
>> okay. So, I wanted to give you guys as
far as public hearings, it seemed like
it was more of a council hearing than a
public hearing. And so, it seemed like
everybody was drowned out um in by the
public because of all the conf uh
council chatter. So, on the public
hearing, if it could be reduced,
especially on a public hearing, you
know, you're going to have another four
weeks to debate this. So, why get in a
fight where the public's supposed to
offer the input instead of um argue
amongst yourself? Um, in regards to like
with the city engineer, I did bring this
up to Councilman Renie and Councilman
Aldridge that um when I was in Nashville
to look at speed cushions as an
alternative um because they won't damage
your snow plows. These are things that
are, you know, rubber that can be set
across the road. Um, and therefore they
can be moved temporarily once the um
habits have changed that it um might be
uh, you know, accessible at a lower
cost, you know, instead of tearing out
roads for speed tables, speed bumps, and
additional uh tri type of traffic um
accommodations that we made going back
to like Mr. Dirkson with uh Pinto Lane.
And my last thing is is um I had asked
Alter Aldrich on um April 30th, my
friend and um you know he wrote a lot of
the code in regards to the tattoo
ordinance. Greg Skebo passed away. And
so I did ask and I'll ask tonight is if
there's a resolution to uh do a
proclamation on April 30th, you know, in
the future to recognize um tattoo
artists for the uh creativity they bring
to Cheyenne's uh not only Jobscape but
you know artistic landscape to uh make a
proclamation and honoring uh Greg Skibo
on April 30th. So if that could be under
consideration, I did tell Dr. Aldrich
that um you know I would write it and
submit it to her if the rest of them. I
did want to u recognize you know that uh
Greg's passing did was a terrible loss
to the tattoo community and you know
what he did for us you know throughout
many many years. So thank you.
>> Thank you Mr. Johnson.
Mr. Miller.
>> Mr. Miller you can unmute yourself.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes Mr. Miller we can hear you.
>> All right. Um uh I just want to start by
saying I appreciated the uh feedback
from the previous speaker. Um
uh but then [clears throat]
also uh I uh I haven't prepared for
anything over three minutes here um
because I usually am lucky to get in a
minute. But um Mr. uh Mr. Mayor, Council
Members, Charles Miller, under other
business, you have spent the night
cutting my microphone and skipping my
turn to hide the fact that this
administration is actively subsidizing
trillion dollar data centers while
crushing Cheyenne's working class.
Tonight, you are you quietly approved
taxpayer funds for AVI Professional
Corporation to design roads, even though
they're the exact agent lobbying to
eradicate hundreds of acres of our
residential land for Microsoft.
You funded Cheyenne leads who claim we
are protected by private CCNRs even
though uh even though recent Finsen FIN
CEN loopholes guarantee those CCNRs are
controlled by completely anonymous shell
companies.
The mayor admitted tonight that he had
to beg a tech CEO for a $3.5 million
bailout just to build a tiny housing
project. Meanwhile, Senator Lumis'
family is cashing out for an estimated
$64 million, selling 3,000 acres to
Microsoft.
You are letting the elite profit while
passing the infrastructure costs onto
the taxpayers.
But the most dangerous thing happening
tonight is the legal advice you're
receiving. City attorney John Brody has
allegedly told this council that my
formal constructive notices don't matter
for your proceedings. I I I can't
remember exactly what the what the exact
quote was. I'll have to go back and look
at that, but but it's uh he said that it
pretty much didn't matter that these uh
formal constructive notices uh weren't
relevant here uh to you guys. And I
strongly advise you to get a second
independent legal opinion. A
constructive notice of fiduciary
misallocation is a formal legal
mechanism establishing that you were
warned prior to voting that you are
misusing public funds and violating your
statutory duties. Your attorney telling
you to ignore it does not magically
shield you from liability when the
financial fallout of this corporate land
grab bankrupts the city. You are
sacrificing Cheyenne's future. Because I
was censored tonight, I am formally
submitting my full objections and my
constructive notices to the city clerk
for the permanent record. Thank you.
Have a good night.
>> Good night, Mr. Miller. Anybody else in
the audience want to speak to us on
other business? How about from the
governing body?
Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, Mayor Collins, I just have a few
items. One, I wanted to make sure that
the community um has heard that the
goats are back. Um, Jennifer was kind
enough to send that to us and that
they're working their way along Crow
Creek. So, if people are wanting to, um,
get sight of those. Um, also wanted to
give a shout out to the community wreck
and events group for a successful first
Friday night on the plaza with no rain,
which was a huge that was a I'm not sure
the weather was all based on their
planning, but um a great turnout and a
great event. Um, Ward 3 council and
coffee will be held on June 20th at
Dosbog from 9 to 11. And um, the Celtic
Festival will be held this upcoming
weekend, the 13th and 14th. Um, so would
invite everybody to check that out if
they're not going to be at Burns Days.
>> Anybody else? Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank [clears throat] you, Mr. Mayor.
Um, I also wanted to thank Jason and his
team for um, Fridays on the Plaza. It
just makes me so happy to go down there
and see so many people of all different
ages. It's it's just great to see the
energy. But um also Saturday I was
downtown for the downtown
>> summer in the street.
>> Summer in the street which there was
tons of people downtown and again all
ages, little kids, lots of treats and
sugar. Um we're making the little kids
real hyper. But um there was people in
all the shops and I just I think it was
really successful. So again, it just
made my heart happy to see that many
people being engaged. So thank you.
>> Anyone else in the governing body?
>> All right, Mr. Seager, do you have a
motion for me?
>> Mr. Mayor, pursuant to Wyoming Statute
section 164405
A10. I move that the governing body meet
in executive session to consider or
receive any information classified
as confidential by law.
Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> All right, that's non-debatable. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> All right, ladies and gentlemen, we're
going to go into executive session. When
we're done, there will be no other
further business of the governing body.
We're just going to adjourn and go home
for a well night, hopefully a good
night's sleep. Um, so we'll ask that the
electronics all be turned off and we'll
close the doors and meet in executive
session.